<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truths testimony and a testimony of truths appearing in power, life, light &amp; glory, creating, manifesting, increasing, and vindicating itself in the midst of persecution : wherein is discovered what truth is, and also a lye, who knows it and lives in it : with the authors call and conversion to the truth, his practice in it, his publishing of it, and his several tryals for the same ... : together with the particular accusations brought against him in each tryal and his answers to the same, and also the courts proceedings both by judges and juries : with an humble appeal to His Highness, Oliver, Lord Protector, as a general redress for all people / by Richard Coppin.</title>
            <author>Coppin, Richard, fl. 1646-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 216 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6105</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12265607</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12265607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">199130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 23:14b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truths testimony and a testimony of truths appearing in power, life, light &amp; glory, creating, manifesting, increasing, and vindicating itself in the midst of persecution : wherein is discovered what truth is, and also a lye, who knows it and lives in it : with the authors call and conversion to the truth, his practice in it, his publishing of it, and his several tryals for the same ... : together with the particular accusations brought against him in each tryal and his answers to the same, and also the courts proceedings both by judges and juries : with an humble appeal to His Highness, Oliver, Lord Protector, as a general redress for all people / by Richard Coppin.</title>
                  <author>Coppin, Richard, fl. 1646-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>With: Divine teachings. 2d. ed. London : William Larner, 1653.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Truthfulness and falsehood.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199130:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Truths Teſtimony; AND A Teſtimony of Truths Appearing, IN <hi>Power, Life, Light &amp; Glory;</hi> Creating, Manifeſting, Increaſing and Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating it ſelf in the midſt of perſecution.</p>
            <p>Wherein is diſcovered what Truth is, and alſo a Lye, who knows it, and lives in it.</p>
            <p>WITH The Authors Call and Converſion to the truth, his practice in it, his publiſhing of it, and his ſeveral Tryals for the ſame: <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Before Baron</hi> Wilde <hi>at</hi> Worceſter.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Before Judge</hi> Nicholas <hi>at</hi> Worceſter.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Before Serjeant</hi> Green <hi>at</hi> Oxford.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Before Serjeant</hi> Hutton <hi>at</hi> Oxford.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Before Serjeant</hi> Glyn <hi>at</hi> Gloceſter.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> The part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cular Accuſations brought againſt him in each Tryal, and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the ſame. As alſo the Courts proceedings both by JUDGES and JURIES.</p>
            <p>With an humble Appeal to his Highneſs, <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector, as a general redreſs for all people.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Coppin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 16.2.</hi>
                  </bibl> They ſhall put you out of the Synagogues; yea, the time cometh, that whoſoever killeth you, will think that he doth God ſervice.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 4.29.</hi>
                  </bibl> But as then, he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even ſo it is now.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> printed, and are to be ſold at the black <hi>Spread Eagle</hi> at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> the <hi>Blackmoores-head</hi> at Fleet bridge, and at the <hi>Seven-ſtars</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:199130:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:199130:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends and Enemies.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the truth of thoſe tranſactions that have paſt between me and my adverſaries may appear, it is through the deſire of many people here publiſhed, as a Narrative of what the Lord in theſe dividing times hath done, and will do, for the encreaſe of the manifeſtation of truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, that through much oppoſition by men living in a lye, againſt thoſe who live in the truth, is the truth made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; concerning which I have not thought my life too dear to have parted with, but with much zeal and love both to God and all people have I been carried on, to vindicate the truth of what was manifeſted to me, and declared by me, who with much joy went through it: I ſtill knowing my ſelf clear and juſtified in and by the Lord and my own conſcience, in all things that I have ſeen, known, and been made a partaker of, in truth and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall queſtion the truth of what is here written in any part of it, it is and will be ready to be proved, not onely by my ſelf, but by ſeveral other perſons that have been hearers of, and eye-witneſſes to the ſame, and that had taken ſeveral Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of what was done in the Courts at my tryals; all which was ſtill recorded and kept to this day, and now publiſhed for the view of all that deſire to look into it, as an outward teſtimony bearing witneſs of the truth againſt all that is a lye in the world.</p>
            <p>And I do further declare that in all my tryals and proceedings to this day, I never feed or bribed any man whatſover, to ſhew me any favour; neither did any ever require it of me, more then what was due by courſe of Law to the Clerks of Aſſizes: for I was not to ſeek to men for any favour, but to leave all to the Lord, whoſe own the cauſe was; and who is and will be made manifeſt in due time to all men, as he is and hath been to him who is ready to ſerve all men in love, while he is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Coppin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <p>SEveral books of the ſame Author now extant; <hi>viz.</hi> one entituled, <hi>Divine Teachings,</hi> in which are three together; a ſecond, <hi>Mans Righteouſneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined;</hi> a third, <hi>Saul ſmitten;</hi> a fourth, <hi>A Man-child born,</hi> and to be ſold with this.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:199130:3"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. 1. <hi>WHat truth is, and what it is not; who knows it and lives in it, &amp;c.</hi> page 1</item>
               <item>Chap. 2. <hi>The Authors life and converſation, before and after the day of his converſion, &amp;c.</hi> page 9</item>
               <item>Chap. 3. <hi>The Authors Call and Commiſſion to preach; what, and from whence it was. The Prieſts Call and Commiſſion to preach,</hi> page 15</item>
               <item>Chap. 4. <hi>The Authors firſt proſecution of his Commiſſion, and his being oppoſed for the ſame, &amp;c.</hi> page 17</item>
               <item>Chap. 5. <hi>The Authors farther proceedings with men in all conditions under their ſeveral Forms and Adminiſtrations, &amp;c.</hi> page 23</item>
               <item>Chap. 6. <hi>The Miniſters malicious proceeding againſt the Author in</hi> Worceſterſhire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> page 27</item>
               <item>Chap. 7. <hi>Of his tryal at</hi> Worceſter <hi>Aſſizes before Baron</hi> Wilde: <hi>the particular accuſations againſt him, and his anſwers to them, &amp;c.</hi> page 31</item>
               <item>Chap. 8. <hi>The Authors ſpeech made to the Judge, after his tryal,</hi> page 44</item>
               <item>Chap. 9. <hi>The Authors ſecond appearing at</hi> Worceſter <hi>Aſſizes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Judge</hi> Nicholas, page 48</item>
               <item>Chap. 10. <hi>The Authors Tryal at</hi> Oxford <hi>Aſſizes before Serjeant</hi> Green: <hi>The particular accuſations againſt him, and his anſwers to them, &amp;c.</hi> page 50</item>
               <item>Chap. 11. <hi>The Authors ſecond appearing at</hi> Oxford <hi>before Judge</hi> Hutton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> page 70</item>
               <item>Chap. 12. <hi>The Authors humble appeal to his Highneſs</hi> Oliver <hi>Lord Protector, as a general redreſs for all people.</hi> page 71</item>
               <item>Chap. 13. <hi>The Sufferings of Chriſt, his Prophets and Apoſtles, with the Authors, preſented to his Highneſs, &amp;c.</hi> page 75</item>
               <item>Chap. 14. <hi>A further diſcovery to his Highneſs, of the malicious practices, ignorant cenſures, and illegal proceedings of two Juſtices and certain Miniſters at</hi> Stow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> page 79</item>
               <item>Chap. 15. <hi>The Authors Tryal at</hi> Gloceſter <hi>Aſſizes before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant</hi> Glyn. page 85</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199130:3"/>
            <head>Truhts Teſtimony; AND A Teſtimony of Truths appearing, In Power, Life, Light and Glory, creating, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting, increaſing and vindicating of it ſelf, in the midſt of Perſecution.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What Truth is, and what it is not; who knows it and lives in it; that it is always perſecuted, and by whom; that it moſt appears, when it is moſt oppoſed; and how.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od that made the world, and all things therein, whoſe goodneſs fills heaven and earth, is holy,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.24, 25, 26, 27, 28</note> juſt and good, the pure, perfect, true God, not confined to time, place, perſon, nor thing; but comprehends in himſelf all things that are, and all things in him that is pure, perfect, true, juſt and good, ſo is to him,
<note place="margin">Titus 1.15.</note> and he cannot behold any thing any otherwiſe then as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199130:4"/>it is in himſelf; who ſees, knows, poſſeſſes and enjoys all things not as man (who is a lyar) but as God (who is true) and who is all,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28.</note> and all in all, in truth and righteouſneſs; and whatſoever (beſides a lye) is or may be ſaid by men not to be in God, and God not to be in that, is a lye; and he that ſaith it, is a lyar; and no lyar can ſtand in the preſence of God, to know Gods preſence with him, till he be brought from the knowledge of a lye, to the knowledge of the truth, as it is in Jeſus, by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of God in Jeſus Chriſt to him:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18, 19.</note> Therefore that which all men are to be, to know, to live in, and to practice in truth and righteouſneſs (that they may no longer be ſhut out from the preſence of God as lyars) is the truth as it is in Jeſus, or God as he is in Chriſt, reconciling the whole world to himſelf, not imputing to any man ſin and tranſgreſſion; and ſo the Lord Jeſus, who is God with us, is to us the way to the truth, the life living in the truth,
<note place="margin">Matth. 1 23. John 14.6.</note> and the truth lived in, that in due time will make manifeſt the freedom of all men in the knowledge of the truth from that which is a lye,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> and bring all men to that which is the truth in himſelf; though in the time of mens falling away from the firſt Image, to have an outward ſhew or form of godlineſs, without the power, they are not brought from the knowledge of a lye, as it is in man, to the knowledge of the truth, as it is in Jeſus. There is nothing more oppoſed, leſs known and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by men living in the knowledge of a lye, yet profeſſing truth and godlineſs,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> then the truth is; <hi>For they profeſs that they know God, but in works they deny him, being abominable and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and unto every good work a reprobate</hi> (as the Scripture ſaith) for all men knowing, owning and living in any thing below God, do ſo long know, own and live in a lye, and ſo are themſelves a lye to themſelves, hating, abominating and oppoſing the truth which they know not; and no lye can know the truth, but the truth knows a lye;
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27.</note> not as a lye, but as the truth: So no man knows God, but God knows man, yet not as man, but as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who knows all things in truth and righteouſneſs, which truth is himſelf:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.5, 6.</note> for he that is all things, cannot know any thing beſides himſelf, there being not any thing but himſelf to be known; elſe how is he all things except a lye? and all the known gods of the Nations which men have worſhipt, and run a whoring after,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199130:4"/>are falſe Gods, and a lye, and a lye is nothing in being; therefore is one God the truth, and all the good that is, is him, for truth and goodneſs live together in God, who is good, and beholds all things good, yea, very good, becauſe he can ſee nothing but what is himſelf; for <hi>there is none good but one, that is God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.17.</note> and yet the whole creation of God is ſaid to be good by God;
<note place="margin">Gen. 1 31. Chap. 2.1, 2.</note> for when he had made all things and finiſhed his work, he beheld it, and ſaw it was very good.</p>
               <p>Therefore is God in Chriſt ſaid to ſee, know, underſtand and judge all things in truth and righteouſneſs, as being all in all things to himſelf,
<note place="margin">1 John 2.21. John 8.44.</note> though the things in themſelves and to men are lyes, yet truth in him and to him, who is all things, and of whom and to whom nothing is a lye; for no lye is of the truth, but all lyes, as lyes, are onely of, and known by the Devil, the great lyar of the world, the deceiver of mankind,
<note place="margin">Iſa 5 20.</note> that turns the truth into a lye, and light into darkneſs, and good into evil, aſcribing that wiſdom, power, will, reaſon, knowledge and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding unto man, which is due to God, ſetting up man in the place of God,
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.4.</note> as knowing and being ſomething elſe beſides God, out of God, that ſo himſelf might have a Kingdom; this is a lye, and the lyar, and the Kingdom of darkneſs; unto which lye and lyar (as unto the Devil and his Kingdom, ſin, hell and damnation) God will not give any place of being out of himſelf to remain, but will turn it again from a lye to the truth, from man to himſelf, from Satan unto God; for he onely is,
<note place="margin">Acts 26.18.</note> and there is none beſides him; ſo that he onely is true, and all things in him are truth.</p>
               <p>Therefore to underſtand the truth, we muſt underſtand and know God, that he onely is that which is to remain, and ſo to underſtand the truth as it is in Jeſus, God in Chriſt manifeſt in fleſh, the Original Centre of all things, that which makes, forms,
<note place="margin">Col. 1 16. Jer 23, 24.</note> creates and fills of its fulneſs all things that were, are, and ever ſhall be in the whole Creation, world without end, himſelf having neither beginning nor end, but is the ſame yeſterday,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13 8.</note> to day, and for ever, and changeth not.</p>
               <p>Therefore is the truth as being the ſame ſtill in God, one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, immortal, incomprehenſible, unlimited,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6 16 1 Tim 1.17</note> indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual, divine being, full of wiſdom, power, life, light and glory,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199130:5"/>or the whole Godhead, acting, ruling and governing all things in the world, and ſo the ſame ſtill at all times, in all places and things, comprehending in it ſelf all things that are in the world as its own, and yet it ſelf not comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not comprehended of, or confined to any one thing, time,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.12.</note> place or perſon, but doth it ſelf make, create and bring forth from it ſelf (as comprehended in it ſelf) all things viſible in the world,
<note place="margin">Rom 1.20</note> as an Image of it ſelf inviſible.</p>
               <p>And this is God, who when he will, can and doth both break in pieces and ſet together again, empty and fill again, wound and heal again,
<note place="margin">Hoſea 6.1.</note> kill and make alive again, all things that are in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in the world, evermore to be changeable in it ſelf, as made, and unchangeable in himſelf as unmade, and he ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to do the ſame, as being an unchangeable workman, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways making,
<note place="margin">Eccle. 1 9.</note> creating and filling all things that are change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: for that which hath been, is that which ſhall be, and that which is done, is that which ſhall be done; and there is no new thing under the Sun, and the beſt of men and things ſo created or made, in the moſt pure, fine, formaliſts outſide appearance of them, are but Images (of the Image of God placed in man) which men would ſet up to worſhip and adore, as <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> did his Image;
<note place="margin">Daniel 3.</note> and they that will not fall down before it, and ſubmit themſelves to it, as to men and their Images, ways, worſhips and opinions, muſt by the decree of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (or the ſame ſpirit of him now appearing amongſt men) be caſt into the hot fiery furnace, made hot by men; that is to ſay, either ſilenced, impriſoned, baniſhed or put to death.</p>
               <p>Therefore what are the beſt of Images to the thing imaged, but vanity and a lye, being as it is changeable? <hi>All is vanity and vexation of ſpirit:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.14.</note> And ſo the beſt of things in its firſt created ſtate, is but an image of the moſt high God, which he onely makes to ſerve its generation, and to paſs away, as we ſee all things do: for man in his upright ſtate, before his fall, was but an Image of God: Religion in the form, is but an Image of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the mind and will; ſo Juſtice and Righteouſneſs in and amongſt men, acted from one to another, is but an Image of what it is in and from God to man; ſo Chriſt himſelf in a humane appearance, as he was man, though he had in him the fulneſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199130:5"/>of the Godhead, yet was he but an Image of the inviſible God,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.15.</note> or the Eternal Being of the Godhead in its Divine ſtate: And all Images are to paſs away, and be removed day by day;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7 31.</note> 
                  <hi>For the faſhion of this world paſſeth away</hi> and whatſoever paſſes away, muſt in that ſtate of mortality be a lye, in oppoſition to that which is immortal and true, becauſe it abides not always the ſame, but is changeable.</p>
               <p>And as a thing made cannot know that which made it; ſo a lye cannot know the truth, nor ſpeak the truth, but as it is in the truth, no longer known to be a lye, but the truth it ſelf:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.11.</note> As nothing therefore but God, who is a Spirit, knows God; ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the truth, knows the truth, nor can ſpeak the truth; and if any thing of truth be ſpoken between man and man,
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.20.</note> it is the truth it ſelf that ſpeaks it ſelf through its own image; for what one man ſpeaks to another in words, is but an Image of the ſame Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpoken to man by the truth in ſilence; for the word in the ſound is but an Image of what is before ſpoken in the mind; &amp; all the writings of men in the letter, is but an Image of the writings of God in the heart and Spirit: So the Scripture, called the Word of God, which are but the writings of men in an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teſtimony,
<note place="margin">John 1.1, 2.</note> is but an Image of the true Word <hi>(Chriſt)</hi> that ſpoke before in them that writ it, and witneſſed to the word by that which is written;
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2, 3, 4</note> for what the Word of God (to wit Chriſt) ſpeaks in men, that man ſpeaks and writes again to men:
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>For what we have ſeen and heard, we declare unto you</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) and all things in the world viſible is but an Image of God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.6.</note> or the things inviſible: and ſo all things, as made, is but an Image of it ſelf as unmade.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> was firſt formed, then <hi>Eve;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2 13, 14.</note> and the woman taken out of man, is but the Image and glory of the man, and lives not but in the man; therefore while ſhe abides in the Image, and is not the ſame with the thing imaged, ſhe abides in a lye, and is in the tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p>So in like manner all mankind, with the whole creation, as coming out of God, is but an Image of God, as the Son is of the Father, and as the woman is of the man, and lives not but in God the Father, that ſends them forth from himſelf as an Image of himſelf, and as it abides in the Image,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.27, 28.</note> and not in him that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199130:6"/>made it, ſo it abides in the lye, and in the tranſgreſſion; and if any would know the truth, in the love of the truth, to ſpeak it, and live in it, they muſt wait to be taken up in the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, into that which is the truth, as Chriſt was; and therein ceaſe in themſelves to ſtand any longer in the Image, but in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as Chriſt did when he did aſcend from the Son to the Father, and ſo muſt become the ſame with the truth, in the truth it ſelf, before they can know what the truth is in the underſtanding of it:
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Iſa. 42.16. I n 2. Epheſ. 1.10.</note> ſo in the chang of all things in man, the woman becomes the man, or weakneſs becomes ſtrength, darkneſs becomes light, death becomes life, and a lye the truth, when the truth hath had its perfect work in making all things free, in turning water into wine, and bringing all things together in one; for the truth is not without a lye;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the man is not without the woman, nor the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man without the man, in the Lord:</hi> So not God without us, nor we without him in the truth, which truth comprehends Father, Son and Spirit, will wiſdom and power, variety in unity, and unity in variety, the Creator and the creature; and ſo God himſelf, who is the truth in Jeſus, who is one and all, is himſelf the way in which all men ſhould walk, the truth which all men ſhould practice,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.6.</note> and the life which all men ſhould live, with Chriſt in God, manifeſt in fleſh; as he is God in union with man, and man in union with God, loving all men as himſelf, doing for all men, as for himſelf, which ſhould be the whole life of all men one to another,
<note place="margin">Matth. 5 44, 45.</note> living in the truth, as it is in Jeſus, even to walk in him as their path, live in him as their life; and ſo to follow his ſteps in the Lord Jeſus,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.1, 2. Acts 17.26. 1 Ioh. 10.11.</note> hating none, ſpeaking evil of none, perſecuting none, but to be friendly, loving, kind and merciful to all, as fleſh of their fleſh, and bone of their bone, being all of one blood, and ſo to forgive one another, as God in Chriſt hath forgiven them: And he who goes any other way, practiſes any other thing,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18, 19. Iohn 14.8. 1 Iohn 1.6, 7, 8.</note> lives any other life, then that which is God living in them and all men, reconciling the whole world to himſelf by Jeſus Chriſt, the way, the truth, and the life, is ſo far a lyar, and the truth is not in him.</p>
               <p>O how few are there that live this life of God in Chriſt, to be reconciled to all men, though enemies; love all men, though enemies; be at peace with all men, though enemies; and to do
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199130:6"/>for all men as they would do for themſelves, and as they would others ſhould do unto them: why very few yet live in the truth to practiſe it, though moſt men profeſs it?</p>
               <p>Therefore all men who live not in the truth are lyars, and live in the filthy abomination of the lye, as in ſin, death, hell, and damnation, wrath, envy, hatred, malice, perſecution, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and all the works of iniquity, and muſt be taken up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the truth, and ſo caſt into the lake of fire burning with brimſtone, there to be purged from all their uncleanneſs and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy abomination,
<note place="margin">Rev. 21 8.</note> that hath defaced the Image of God as to men, before they can be lovers of God or the truth, and ceaſe from perſecuting one another.</p>
               <p>All things while it abides in the Image, being there in a priſon, and in darkneſs, is an enemy to the thing imaged, becauſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents it not perfectly, or as it is in Jeſus: the thing made is an enemy to that which makes it, the creature to the Creator,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.9.4, 5, 6, &amp;c.</note> man to God; for all men, as men and ſinners, ſo remaining, are haters of God, and do oppoſe the truth in the manifeſtation: But the more truth is oppoſed,
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.10, 11, 12.</note> the more will it increaſe in power, and break forth in the light of its manifeſtation, to thoſe that are oppoſed, and alſo for the good of thoſe that do op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, though for a time it may be hid from their eyes.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that betrayed and murther'd Chriſt and his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Iohn 16.2, 3.</note> thought they did God ſervice, and themſelves good (and ſo they did) though they knew it not, in perſecuting, reviling, ſtoning and killing blaſphemers (as they ſaid) againſt God; but they knew neither God, them, nor the blaſphemy they charged them with; for had they known Chriſt, they would not have put him to death, nor crucified the Lord of glory, as they did;
<note place="margin">Act. 3.17, 18</note> yet this did bring glory to God, and good to all his people: for through death did he aſcend into the glory of his Father,
<note place="margin">Iohn 14.3.</note> in which glory he returned again to his people, to take them to himſelf, that where he was, they might be alſo;
<note place="margin">Iohn 12.32.</note> and (ſaith he) <hi>If I be lifted up, I will draw all men unto me.</hi> not onely Scribes and Phariſees, but Publicans and ſinners, when the Scribes and Phariſees thought it had belong'd onely to themſelves, as righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men, and not unto ſinners;
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.19.</note> and becauſe he was a friend to all, even ſinners, as well as them, therefore ſought they the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:199130:7"/>more to kill him: yet his love was ſtill the ſame, both to them and all others, though enemies to him; for ſaith he, of thoſe betrayed him and took his life from him,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther, forgive them, they know not what they do;</hi> and the more they ſought to betray him, the more did the people follow him, and grew in love with him: and men can never do any thing more to the loſs of their own honour, Religion and ſelf-intereſts, and more to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the truth in the life and power of it, then to oppoſe it, and perſecute it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for then do men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he more enquire after it, and truth will have its perfect work, and find out a way to advance it ſelf in the greateſt perſecution, though men never ſo much oppoſe it. Therefore when men go to ſtop the current of truth, and the mouthes of thoſe that declare it, by an outward Law, they do but as thoſe that go to make a dam to ſtop the current of a continual running ſtream, which will ſuddenly make its way through it, and carry all before it: Or, as thoſe who go to throw oyl and brimſtone to quench fire that is burning, which the more they do, the more it will flame and burn to the deſtruction of that which is thrown into it to quench it: So is it with truth, when it ariſes in life and power to manifeſt it ſelf,
<note place="margin">Iſa 27.4.</note> nothing is or ſhall be then able to ſtand againſt it, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the growth and increaſe of it; but it will drive all before it that ſhall ſtand in the way of it: and as fire among thorns, ſo will it burn, waſte, conſume and bring to nothing, all that which is abomination, and a lye, in the world, that nothing hereafter ſhall be ſeen to ſtand in the high place of God; but himſelf will there ſhew himſelf to be all in all, as he is the One and the All, the All and the One, though not yet manifeſt unto all men.</p>
               <p>Therefore, O man, thou that wouldſt not have the truth to ſpread, which thou knoweſt not, ceaſe any longer to oppoſe it, if thou canſt forbear, for through much oppoſition is the truth made manifeſt, and God would not be ſaid to be a conqueror, if there were not ſomething of a lye in oppoſition to the truth to be conquered; for were there no oppoſition known in men to oppoſe God, there would be in men no need of the knowledge of the coming of God in Chriſt to men, to oppoſe againſt that: for his coming to manifeſt himſelf, is to reconcile his enemies to himſelf, and to deſtroy that which is enmity in them againſt him;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199130:7"/>for, <hi>for this purpoſe was the ſon of God manifeſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>to deſtroy the works of the devil:</hi> and men in looking upon God to be at a diſtance from them through the temptations of Satan, do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by oppoſe his preſence with them; for God is nigh them,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 28.</note> with them and in them, as one reconciled to them, and all things in the world with them, though they know it not; and this is mans deſtruction, not to know God, as God knows man,
<note place="margin">Hoſea 4 6.</note> but to live as one without God in the world, always fearing of God as an angry God; and ſo kept at a diſtance from God,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.7.</note> by being ignorant of God; as <hi>always learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth;</hi> neither can, till they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the light of God in their own conſciences, to ſee God with them, reſtoring reſt and peace to them, and himſelf to be in them the way, the truth, and the life for them; unto the end of which way, the knowledge of which truth, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which life, all men have a race to run and a way to come, before they can ſit down at the end of their journey, and live in the knowledge of the truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors Life and Converſation before and after the day of his Converſion; the manner of his converting, and his zeal in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, trying and paſſing by all the Ways, Worſhips and Opinions of men, in their ſeveral Forms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f Religion; howmen appeared in it; how it all vaniſhed away and ceaſed, as to him; and when.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>HEarken my beloved brethren, come behold, and ſee the race which you are to run, the way which you are to come, and the price that is to be wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as I will here ſhew unto you, by ſetting before you the race that I have run,
<note place="margin">Phil 3. 1 Cor. 9.14.</note> the way that I have gone, and the price that I have won; wherein if the Lord will, you may behold the manner and courſe of my life, and the dealings of God with me all along, from the time he firſt created me and brought me forth of my mothers womb, to this day; and that you by comparing with it the manner and courſe of your
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199130:8"/>life, and the dealings of God with you, may ſee how near a progreſs you have made to this price,
<note place="margin">Job 42.5.</note> the fathers Kingdom, and end of your journey. God himſelf, attainable in this life; after which there is no more travelling, but you are ſet down, and at reſt with the ſon in the boſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m of the Father And<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, when once I came to this ſtate of the meaſure of the gift of Chriſtin me, I then was in a ſtate to ſee God as he is, and the truth as it is in Jeſus, made manifeſt in my fleſh, and ſo was made to look back upon what I had ſeen, and formerly been from the day of my creation, to the day of my converſion, which the light of God within me did ſhew unto me, that I repented of, and was changed from my former life I lived, in the time of my ignorance; and which by the light of God in me, I ſhall here ſhew unto you.</p>
               <p>For when God created me in my mothers womb, and breathed into me the breath of life, that I became a living ſoul, I was in a ſtate of innocency, knowing neither good nor evil; or as <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.7.</note> and as all men elſe are when they are firſt created, and live; but I quickly fell from this innocent ſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, to the knowledge of good and evil, as to the ſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> after his fall, ſinful and wicked, and taking my own pleaſure in all manner of ſports and delights for outward recreation of the creature, without any true knowledge of the Creator, which for many years I would have gone many miles after, caring for no Religion at all neither did I know what it was, onely I heard of a God afar off, one that lived above the skies, ſitting in a golden chair, and was like my ſelf, which the Prieſts and people did talk of, as one that loved thoſe that did well, and hated others that did ill; and would at the laſt day come to judge me and all men according to their works (but I knew him not, but by hear-ſay, according to the common talk of people) and that his worſhip conſiſted in mens &amp; womens going to Church, and ſuch like ſervice (but not childrens) and that this holineſs conſiſted in abſtaining from ſwearing, drunkenneſs, thieving, whoring, and ſuch like ſins; which ſins being not committed by me, I thought ſufficient to ſave me, being taught ſo by (our Teachers) the Prieſts of thoſe times, who them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as well as others, committed all manner of ſin and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and who deceived both me and many thouſands of ſouls
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199130:8"/>by their deluſions, but never taught us of a Jeſus, all this while, neither could they, becauſe they knew him not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; yet God was there with them under this diſpenſation, though vailed, and in a cloud;
<note place="margin">Pſal 97.2.</note> for clouds and darkneſs are round about him: but theſe clouds in ſome meaſure vaniſhing, as to me, I paſt them by, and preſt forwards.</p>
               <p>And now having lived for many years in this ſtate of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, under the Biſhops and Prelatical Government; I then came to the Presbyterians, who began to reign in the others ſteads, exerciſing the ſame authority over mens conſciences as the other did; and who after ſome ſhort time I found to rule with as much force and cruelty, and to be as tyrannical as ever the others were, and that knew no more of God then the others did; onely they would talk a little more of Chriſt and Religion, uſing the outward expreſſions as a cloak to cover their nakedneſs, and to ſeduce the people to them: but for any true knowledge of Chriſt and Religion, they had none, neither any did they practiſe; yet here was God likewiſe, but ſtill in a cloud, under darkneſs, that I paſſed by them alſo, and preſſed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>And I being yet willing to try all things; and I hearing of the Independants and Anabaptiſts ſtarting up, as thoſe that would reign in the room of the Presbyterians, I would try them alſo; and found them to be cloathed with a more finer habit then either Prelate or Presbyterian; for they had gained ſome finer outſide forms of Religion,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.7.</note> decked over more with Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture terms, as cloaks, or figleaves to cover their nakedneſs: and called them the Ways and Ordinances of Chriſt, or at leaſt, put that name upon them, to take away their reproach,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 4.</note> though they were ſtill their own, and of their own inventions: for, as uſed by them, they are not according to the inſtitution of Chriſt in the primitive times, as they think they are: wherefore they do but cheat themſelves &amp; others, having no true knowledg of God all this while, but by hearſay,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.7, 8.</note> and what they gain one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by their outſide Forms, Ways, and Religious duties, which they are to count all loſt for Chriſt; and in which I beheld them and all the reſt of men, with all their differing Ways, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Opinions to be in all things ſuperſtitious and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous,
<pb facs="tcp:199130:9"/>as <hi>Paul</hi> did the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>emans And ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſpace of two years,
<note place="margin">Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 17.21, 22, 23.</note> beholding this their order in <hi>London</hi> ſeeing all to be but diſorder and confuſion I paſſed them all be, and preſt forwards to the mark, for the price of the high calling of God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hriſt Jeſus; which is a calling above all things whatſoever, as of Presbytery, Independency, Anabaptiſm, and whatſoever calling elſe any man may now pretend to live; yet this is a calling above them all, which none of theſe have yet attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o live.</p>
               <p>In which two years time before mentioned, of walking among the Churches in <hi>London,</hi> of Presbyterians, Independents and Anabaptiſts &amp;c. I applyed my ſelf much to reading their books, ſearching and trying the Scriptures, whether theſe things they held were ſo or no, and to be ſo practiſed by them as they were, and contended for, which I found them not to be: Alſo in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving duties of prayer was I very frequent morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and as often as I had opportunity: and in hearing or writing of Sermons four or five in a day, from ſeveral men, which I ſpent much of my time after in reading.</p>
               <p>Thus was I in that time, while I was trying their ways, as zealous as they could be in it, even hating, loathing and deſpiſing all my own, and other mens former ways, delights, pleaſures and ſports, and all delightful exerciſes: which I was not ſo much for before, but then I was as much againſt, counting them all to be but works of darkneſs, while they were ſo acted; yet was my ſelf ſtill (though under this diſpenſation of Grace) as blind and as ignorant as ever I was under that of nature, though I thought I ſaw and had knowledge: but I found ſince, that all the light and knowledge that I then thought I had of God, Chriſt, and the Devil, of Heaven and Hell, Salvation and Damnation, with all things elſe thereto belonging in that ſtate of ignorance, was as carnal as ever; and I knew no more of it then I did when I was under the Prelates Miniſtry; only that there was a God afar off and not within me, which I ſtill knew but by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, as all that were of thoſe opinions did; and therefore I may be bold to affirm, as alſo by experience I have known, that all the knowledge that Presbyterians. Independents, Anabaptiſts, and all others under any form of Worſhip, now have of thoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199130:9"/>things, while living under the diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſation of grace (only) while ſeeking the Lord is no more then but by hear-ſay, which they ſo long give themſelves to believe, and are in bondage to, as to mens traditions; and no experience at all have they of theſe things, as to know them in truth, or as it is in Jeſus. And this was all the knowledge and experience that I had, while un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that diſpenſation of grace, or the Son of God manifeſting (yet the ſame that they had) where I then ſaw the work but a doing, not done; ſalvation but a coming, and not come, and ſo ſaw not any thing then made perfect.</p>
               <p>Then after two years were expired of my beholding this their order in <hi>London,</hi> ſeeing all the ways and opinions of men, with all their feigned righteouſneſs, for to be but deſtruction and confuſion, I propheſied of their downfall, which would ſhortly after come to paſs, and which I have ſince, in part, ſeen to be fulfilled; for I ſaw that they were not built upon the true foundation. Chriſt, as the rock which would ſtand,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11.</note> and was laid by God; but upon the foundation and buildings of men,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.26, 27.</note> laid by men on the ſands, as that which would ſhake and fall, and would not endure the fire, even God when he appeared, but would, with all their Elements, melt before him as droſs,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.10.</note> and with all their fair heavens be burnt up before him as ſtubble, and vaniſh away before him as ſmoak, and as chaff before the wind: Wherefore I ſeeing them to be thus fitted for deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and prepared for the ſlaughter, I paſſed them all by, that I might not in my profeſſion be deſtroyed with them, and would not go in, or be tyed in covenant to any of them, being none of them according to the inſtitution of Chriſt; and they being thus weighed in the ballance of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, by Chriſt, and there found too light, they vaniſhed away, and ſo ceaſed, as to me.</p>
               <p>And after this legal diſpenſation of the knowledge of Chriſt in the fleſh, and the performing duties after the fleſh, by me, was ended with me,
<note place="margin">John 16.25.</note> and Chriſt appearing in power and glory to me; ſhewing me plainly of the Father, I then ſaw according to that appearance of God to me in the Father, what and where God, Chriſt and the Devil was, and is, alſo heaven and hell, ſalvation and damnation, what and where that was, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199130:10"/>is, I having had the experience of it all within me; and ſo I ſaw, as to my ſelf, a death of the one part, as of the Devil, hell and damnation, with all things, at the left hand of God; and a living of the other part, as of God, Chriſt, Heaven and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, with all things, at the right hand of God; which was my dying to the one part, as to that on the left hand; and my living to the other part, as to that on the right hand, and which was to me the day of the Lord, and a reſtauration of all things to God; where, and at which time I ſaw one diſpenſation per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in another, or grace perfected in glory, the Son perfected in the Father, or all things made perfect in God, the Kingdom of the Son delivered up to the Father;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.21.</note> and where I ſaw all my own works, which ever I had done under any diſpenſation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that of Chriſt in the Spirit, to be burnt up and made void to me, with all my prayers which I made, books which I had read, ſermons which I had heard, beſides and below Chriſt, all now appeared to be of no worth unto me,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.9. &amp; 3 9.</note> as to do me any good; for I had found one Jeſus, that was aſcended far above all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, that he might fill all things, and that had a name above every name that was named, of things in heaven, and of things on earth; in whom I was now found, without having my own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, who was now become my worth, my life, my light, and my all, who had filled me with himſelf, and whom I ſaw to be all to me, and to do all for me, and to have given an end to all things beſides himſelf in me; which made me now throw away all my books of Presbyterians, Independants, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,
<note place="margin">Acts 19.18, 19.</note> and whatſoever elſe (as the believing Jews and Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had done before) and to forget all things therein, and not to know any thing any where, or in any thing, either without or within me, but Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified; and ſo to know my ſelf in him, to have made my progreſs to him in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingdom, the end of my journey, where I ſhall no more be travelling, but be at reſt with the Son, in the boſom of the Father: Which is the race that all men are to run, the way that all men are to go, and the work that all men are to do, even to deny themſelves,
<note place="margin">Luke 9.23, 24.</note> and all things of themſelves, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, till they come to Chriſt, if ever they mean to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199130:10"/>with Chriſt: for, <hi>If thou wilt be perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note> 
                  <hi>go and ſell all that thou haſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors Call and Commiſsion to preach; what, and from whence it was; the Pariſh Prieſts Call and Commiſsion to preach, what, and from whence that was.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen God in Chriſt did manifeſt himſelf to me for my converſion, the redemption of my body, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my ſoul, to the perfecting of the body of Chriſt in and to me, as that I knew it, and was aſſured of it in my ſelf, what, and when it vvas: I then ſavv it all to be in him, the ſame to all men as to me, though not manifeſt unto them; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to vvhat I had received of the Lord. I vvas command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord in me, to publiſh and declare to all ſorts of men, vvithout reſpect of perſons or opinions, vvith this Commiſſion follovving:</p>
               <p>Firſt, that vvhatſoever I did ſpeak or vvrite, it vvas to be my ovvn experience in the Lord, of God manifeſt in fleſh, juſtified in the ſpirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on in the World, received up into glory, Chriſt the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever. And that I was not to ſpeak or write any thing that ſhould tend to the continuing,
<note place="margin">John 6.27.</note> advancing or ſetting up of any thing that ſhould periſh or come to an end, and be in oppoſition to the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſus, as the ſetting up of any thing beſides him was; but that it ſhould always tend to the advancement of his Kingdom, as of love, joy, peace and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs among men through Chriſt; and to the throwing down of Antichriſt and his Kingdom, with all deceiveableneſs and unrighteouſneſs of men: and what I did. I was to do it free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in love, and not be chargeable or burthenſome to any,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> to hinder any from coming into the Kingdom of the Lord, which was a free Kingdom; nor to give any liberty to Antichriſts Kingdom, which was a Kingdom of gain, hire, and ſelf inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and which conſiſts of buying and ſelling the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:199130:11"/>and for which work the Lord would be with me,
<note place="margin">Acts 18.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14 15, 16</note> to ſupport me to the end, as he was with <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Corinth;</hi> and by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I have hitherto found him to be with me.</p>
               <p>And thus was my Commiſſion in &amp; from the School of Chriſt, given by Chriſt at <hi>Sion</hi> houſe in heaven, to do the work of Chriſt as a free workman, loving all men, though enemies, and hating none and not from <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> or the Schools of Antichriſt, by the laying on of the hands of the Biſhops or Presbytery, to do the work of Antichriſt as an hireling, loving thoſe that would pay me or ſtand for me, and hating thoſe that would not, as moſt of thoſe have done that had their Call and Commiſſion from thence: Neither was I to confer with fleſh and blood, as to go to <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> this Committee or that Committee, to receive Orders from men, or to know whether I ſhould preach or no, and ſo to be ſettled in ſome place by them, receive ſome yearly maintenance from them, as the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> do, and have done with all that ſerve in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts Kingdom, and receive his wages but without all this, or any part of it, I was immediately to go and publiſh him to the world, and to ſinners, yea all men, without reſpect of perſons, notwithſtanding all the oppoſition that I might meet withal from all ſorts of Religion, and among all ſorts of men living under any Diſpenſation or Adminiſtration whatſoever, below this which I my ſelf lived in, and was to declare.</p>
               <p>And the firſt day that I began to proſecute this my Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it was in me in the life and power of it (which I received not of man, nor by man, but of and by the Lord, and God the Father, who raiſed him from the dead, out of the grave, and in me) then was I perſecuted, hated and rejected of men that knew it not, but were enemies to it; yet did no more to me, then what had been done to others that were before me, and will be done to thoſe that come after me; which I alſo looked upon to be part of my portion which was to follow and I to go through, and which I was yet to be poſſeſt withal while I was in this work of preaching: but knowing this that ſtill filling up the reſt of the ſufferings of Chriſt, which ſupported me, when I had finiſhed my courſe, I ſhould receive my crown; <hi>Having ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with Chriſt, I ſhould alſo reign with him;</hi> and ſo enduring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199130:11"/>to the end, I ſhould be ſaved,
<note place="margin">Mar. 13.13 1 Cor. 9.17 18. 2 Cor. 10.16, 17.</note> and this was my portion alſo with the Lord, and the reward I received of the Lord, and is a living on the Goſpel, with me; as it is written, <hi>He that preaches the Goſpel, ſhall live on the Goſpel,</hi> and not on other mens labours, nor walk by other mens lights, but the light of Chriſt in the Goſpel diſpenſation: And now ſo far hitherto as I have fell ſhort in any thing of this my Commiſſion, to the knowledge of any, let me be blamed.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, I ſhall go on as brief as I can to ſhew you the manner of my proceedings, and how I have been carried forth to this day, as ſhall be readily witneſſed by the people of thoſe parts in which I have been, and thus proceeded in the practice thereof, as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors firſt proſecution of his Commiſsion, and his being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the ſame; how, by whom, and after what manner; who are the Miniſters of Chriſt, and of Antichriſt, with their different proceedings, both in judgement, doctrine, practice, manner, time, place, freedom and reward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>FIrſt, <hi>Paul</hi> in his time ſpeaking of himſelf and his own call, ſaid then, <hi>That above fourteen years ago he knew a man in Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>whether in the body, or out of the body, he could not tell, but ſuch an one caught up into the third heaven,</hi> or paradiſe, <hi>and heard unſpeakable words, which were not lawful for man to utter:</hi> And why unlawful? In reſpect of the Lavv of God it could not be unlavvful; for God reveals nothing that is contrary to himſelf, or his ovvn lavv, neither doth he make a lavv contrary to vvhat he reveals: but it might be contrary to the lavvs of men, vvhich they had made, and do ſtill make, and ſo unlavvful; and in this ſenſe <hi>Paul</hi> might ſay, it vvas unlavvful for man to utter, though not unlavvful for God to utter: and for theſe reaſons; firſt, in reſpect of the company amongſt whom <hi>Paul</hi> vvas then living, vvhen thoſe vvords vvere made knovvn to him, they being not able to bear them: And ſecondly, it may be that the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199130:12"/>lavvs of the times vvere ſuch, that if it ſhould have been ſpoken, it vvould have been counted blaſphemy, and himſelf have been perſecuted for it, as it ſeems he vvas for many things that he then ſpoke: And ſo in all ages ſince, vvhatever of God hath by God been revealed to men, contrary to the lavv of the times, hath been by that lavv unlavvful to utter, and ſo by men count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed blaſphemy, and the authors thereof accuſed as blaſphemers. Was it not ſo vvith Chriſt, and vvith <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles? And hath it not been ſo ſince? and is it not ſo novv? I am ſure my ſelf with many others, can by experience witneſs it, and ſet our ſeals to it, ſince we knew it, and were aſſured of it.</p>
               <p>And now from the time that theſe things were firſt made known to me, and I commanded to declare it to the world, it was with much oppoſition, and with ſo little outward freedom, that I was forced to appear in the clouds, and ſpeak ſomething darkly, and under parables, I abiding at that time in <hi>Barkſhire,</hi> among a people whoſe ſpirits were not able to bear the ſound of the truth, they being ignorant of it, and ſo enemies to it; and which the laws of the times were then againſt, and moſt mens judgements and opinions contrary to it, and men more ready to perſecute it, then otherways, as they have ever been. And I having not my freedom to ſpeak, fell a writing; which things were printed, and brought forth to publique view, in a Book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Divine Teachings;</hi> which many Miniſters and Paſtors of Churches living thereabouts, did ſtreightway oppoſe, being that which was contrary to their judgements, doctrine and practiſe; whoſe names are as follows, <hi>Lancaſter, Powel, Harriſon, Pendar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, Wells, Hughes,</hi> and <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> who were then in <hi>Barkſhire;</hi> with <hi>Osburn, Woolly, Glin,</hi> and many others in <hi>Oxfordſhire;</hi> who cryed down all for hereſie and blaſphemy therein contained, without naming any particulars, ſaying it was a dangerous prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple which it all tended unto, that if it were ſuffered, it would overthrow all <hi>(Mens)</hi> Religion; whereupon ſeveral diſputes were occaſioned between me and the ſaid Miniſters; they all ſtill endeavouring to confute me, or bring me to a recantation of theſe things revealed in me, and declared by me, which they counted erroneous and blaſphemous; and of which if I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199130:12"/>would have recanted, preferment by ſome was proffered me; but there was one within me which reſiſted, and ſaid, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan,</hi> I will none of it: neither is it <hi>Herod</hi> with all the chief of the Prieſts and Scribes of the people, that he had gathered together, that can deſtroy the childe Jeſus after once he is born; nor could theſe with all their ſubtilty, deſtroy that which was born in me, or bring me to a recantation of what I had declared, that I immediately departed out of theſe coaſts, and ſaw much of God in it; for I went ſtrait abroad publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame things with boldneſs, both in writing and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in ſeveral Countreys where I was deſired to come. And there living in that Countrey of <hi>Barkſhire,</hi> where I firſt began to publiſh theſe things, a man of eminency in the world, whom the Prieſts knew to be zealous for them and their ways, and they having not prevailed with me to write a recantation of thoſe things I held, they then prevailed with him to joyn with them in buying up as many as they could get of the foreſaid books, (entituled, <hi>Divine Teachings</hi>) in which thoſe things were publiſhed, that they might ſpread no farther amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; of which books they bought to the value of about ten pounds worth, having no other way to ſtop them, and which the Prieſts would have had him to have burned; but he was wiſer then ſo; and ſaid, that he would rather keep them for waſte paper, and did not know but that they might yield him his money again, if the things ſhould after come in requeſt; but however, theſe books are again reprinted, and the things therein ſtill maintained by me, being the ſame in me.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee how ſome men, out of zeal to their own opinions, and others for lucre of gain, not yet knowing the truth, will endeavour to binder the ſpreading of truth, and ſo through ignorance and blind zeal, will turn perſecutors of Chriſt, his Kingdom, and the Righteouſneſs thereof.</p>
               <p>This Kingdom of Chriſt, and all things therein, as love, joy, peace, life, light, heaven, and ſalvation in Chriſt alone, I ever ſince I knew it, and taſted of it, have not ceaſed to write of, publiſh and declare in ſeveral Countreys,
<note place="margin">Acts 28.30, 31.</note> both in publique and private, from houſe to houſe, in their Churches, Streets and Market places, where the Lord hath been pleaſed to carry
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199130:13"/>me, and where people deſired me to come and were aſſembled together to hear me, I never deſiring to be chargeable to any, to hinder any from coming into the Kingdom of the Lord, which is a free Kingdom;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9 12, 18, 19.</note> neither would I ever yield to take any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward maintenance from any upon that account of preaching, for that was but Antichriſts hire, in Antichriſts Kingdom, which moſt men yet have appeared to live in, nay, the pureſt Churches of Independents and Anabaptiſts, as well as Prelates and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians which though they have not all took tythes, they have took money or moneys worth; and ſo cannot ſay, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>I have coveted no mans gold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 20.33</note> 
                  <hi>ſilver, or apparel:</hi> which is all but Antichriſts pay, in Antichriſts Kingdom, to Antichriſts ſervants, whoſe ſervants all are that preach for gain or hire, and not for pure love to Chriſt and all people:
<note place="margin">John 10.8.10.</note> and Chriſt ſaith of the hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that they are but Thieves and Robbers, and fly when he that is free cometh; and this would quickly be maniefeſt, were but tythes and the Prieſts hire put down, and every one have freedom to preach that could; I will warrant you that thoſe Preachers that were ſent from <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> would quickly fly from you, leave you, and preach no more to you, and yet you would have more Preachers then are now: for then every one that had received any thing of God, would freely declare it; and this would be according to the Goſpel rule, which ſaith, <hi>When thou art converted, ſtrengthen thy brother;</hi> and, <hi>As every man hath received the gift, ſo let them adminiſter one to another;</hi> and not one to forbid another: for let one that preaches freely come into the Church or Pariſh of him that preaches for hire, and the hireling will preſently forbid the freeman; ſaying, this is my houſe and my Pariſh (or Foxes hole) you ſhall not preach here:
<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th 8 20.</note> and though the men of the Pariſh (to wit, the Maſter) would have him yet the ſervant forbids him: And doth not the ſervant here exalt himſelf above the Maſter, the Prieſt above the people? but ſurely <hi>he that exalts himſelf ſhal be brought low, and he that humbles himſelf ſhall be exalted;</hi> and it is enough that the ſervant be as his Maſter, and not above his Maſter, though it hath been ſo hitherto between the people and their Miniſters. What is the Church but the Town-houſe, in which the Prieſt, the Town-ſervant, is to do the Towns work, for which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199130:13"/>he receives the Towns wages? And what if the Maſter be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that the ſervant ſhould ſit ſtill, and ſet another to do his work notwithſtanding the ſervant ſhall ſtill have his wages? O but here is a ſlaviſh fear in the ſervant, that if another ſhould do his work better then him, it would be to his diſgrace; and more then that if the maſter ſhould once find that he could have his work done freely, he would then hire no more; and what would then become of the hireling? he muſt pack up and be gone: and ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi>The hireling flyeth, becauſe he is an hireling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 10.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and careth not for the ſheep. I am the good Shepherd</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and know my ſheep, and am known of mine:</hi> And ſure Chriſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver preached for hire, nor any that ever he ſent, that ever I read of in Scripture: then thoſe that do, were never ſent by him, but by his enemy the Devil, or Man of Sin, to keep up a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom contrary to his: and it is very likely, that the Man of Sin is their Maſter that ſent them, becauſe they ſo much preach up ſin unpardoned, which is the keeping up of his Kingdom in which they live, and without which they could not live, as to keep up that trade of buying and ſelling the Word of God: for they live by telling the people of their ſins,
<note place="margin">Jer. 5.30, 31.</note> and ſome people love to have it ſo, who live in the ſame Kingdom with them, and that love to pay them.</p>
               <p>But in the Kingdom of Chriſt, which is a free Kingdom, there is no ſuch thing; there is no ſin unpardoned, therefore no tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the people ſo, neither do the people there love to have it ſo: but there is all ſin pardoned for all men, paſt, preſent, and to come; and thoſe that are ſent by Chriſt, and that live in that Kingdom, come with that meſſage in their mouthes, That all ſin is pardoned, and all men forgiven,
<note place="margin">Dan. 9.24.</note> ſin and tranſgreſſion finiſhed, and everlaſting Righteouſneſs brought in by Chriſt alone: and this is my meſſage which I have to all the world, and which I am to deliver freely, and for which thoſe that have not the ſame meſſage to deliver, do hate me, and perſecute me: but I paſſed them all by, and would not be partaker of their ſins; and he that hath kept me hitherto, keeps me ſtill, that I may not do Antichriſts work, neither receive Antichriſts wages, or live by the ſins of the people, as ſome others do.</p>
               <p>But ſome may ſay, Did you never receive any money for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199130:14"/>preaching? I anſwer, I never received any that ever I put in my own purſe; but where there was money appointed for preaching, and no Prieſt there to challenge it as his proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that either I muſt diſpoſe of it, or others whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned not, muſt put it in their own purſes, I gave order that the poor of each Pariſh might have it, as will be witneſſed in ſeveral places:
<note place="margin">Acts 20.33, 34, 35.</note> and therefore can ſay with <hi>Paul, I have co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted no mans ſilver, or gold, or apparel:</hi> yet of this will I not glory, but I will glory in the Lord, who hath ſo far kept me from being a hireling in Antichriſts Kingdom, that he will rather make all my ways appear more for the abominating and throwing down of all ſuch Antichriſtian ways of maintenance, then for the ſetting of it up; for which the Prieſts, and all Impropriators, with all that live in that and the like mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that knew me, or had heard of me, could never abide me, but always perſecuted me, ſought for my impriſonment, baniſhment or ſilencing, and alſo my life. While I was thus carried forth in contending for the truth, yet was I ſtill rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſpend and be ſpent for the good of all people, even my enemies; and was more ready to give then to receive, according to my ability,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.15. Acts 20.35.</note> and ſo ſtill at peace in my ſelf, through all things with Chriſt in God, that ever I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took, and went through by him, in all my proceedings, to this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199130:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors further proceedings in his dealings with men in all conditions, under their ſeveral Forms and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: That his Doctrine never tended to draw men to any Opinion under any one Form of Worſhip; but to preſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the life of God in Chriſt, above the Whoriſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Vanities of the World; that to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace, and Love with all men, having peace with God, is the pure Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ANd now the manner of my farther dealings in Judgement and Doctrine with men in all conditions, under their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Forms, Adminiſtrations or Diſpenſations, was ſtill a preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them forwards after Chriſt, to the knowledge of the truth as it is in Jeſus, and not a ſtaying of men any where, or endeavouring to draw men to any Form, Way, Worſhip or Opinion from Chriſt; neither to rail againſt any man of any opinion whatſoever, but to ſpeak the truth to all, ſhewing what all thoſe opinions of men are, and what, and where they themſelves are, while under them; and how they are to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all, and follow Chriſt, be they Prelates, Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, or whatſoever opinion elſe may be found out by man beſides Chriſt, all are to paſs away; and they are to paſs them all by, as by ſo many harlots houſes,
<note place="margin">Prov. 7.</note> ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the ways ſide, by which poor ſouls are to paſs, before they come to their reſt; and into which, as into ſo many Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes or Taverns, many thouſand of poor ſouls are allured and drawn aſide to eat, and to drink, and commit fornication with the Inhabitants thereof, neglecting their journey to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> or Mount-<hi>Sion;</hi> and where, for ſome time, they take up their reſt, that many paſs by them, and get into heaven before them, while they are feaſting with harlots,
<note place="margin">Rev. 17.14, 15.</note> the daughters of the great Whore that ſits upon many waters, and on the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of mens holineſs, eating bread, and drinking wine, until the Lord come to feaſt with them there, and by a ſtrong hand overcome them, pull them down, or bring them forth, and ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199130:15"/>lead them on, carrying them by all thoſe opinions of men, onely to knock at their doors, as ſome have done before look in upon them, and behold their devotion; but not to go into them,
<note place="margin">Prov. 7.27.</note> leſt they ſhould be devoured by them: <hi>For their houſe is the way to hell, going down to the chambers of death:</hi> Therefore let not your hearts be inclined to their ways, go not aſtray in their pathes, leſt you ſhould ſtay or be ſeduced by them: But ſay, friends, come away, this is not your reſt, ariſe, depart, for it is polluted, and if you ſtay, it will deſtroy you with a ſore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;
<note place="margin">Micah 2.10.</note> This ſay unto them, but go not in; for if you go in to them, the Devil will come and take you, make you drunk, and there cauſe you to ſtay, and ſo make you become Devils with him, or them, to accuſe and perſecute, eat, devour and condemn one another, or all that come not in to you and be the ſame with you in your opinions: Therefore I adviſe you not to ſtay any where,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.1, 2.</note> nor to ſet your minds, deſires and affections up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any thing below Chriſt, in the way you are to go to Chriſt; but ſtill in all this your worſhipping of God (as you call it) to preſs forwards to the mark,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus; where you will then reſt, be at peace, and be ſatisfied, and where you will no more accuſe, perſecute, judge, devour and condemn one another, as you do; but where you will be reconciled in love one to another, and to all men, though your greateſt enemies.</p>
               <p>And this is the advice that I give to all men, in all that I ſay unto them, to preſs forwards to the knowledge of the truth, as it is in Jeſus; and I do not go about to ſet up any thing below the Lord Jeſus, nor to draw men to any opinion of things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him; but to ſhew them the vanity and nothingneſs of all the ways and opinions of men below him, declaring what they are in themſelves, and their places, ſhewing that they are but notions, and ſo mens inventions, ſhadows dying vanities, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting pleaſures, things that would periſh, and come to an end with the uſing, after the commandments and doctrines of men;
<note place="margin">Job 14.14.</note> yet never declared againſt them, ſo as to forbid any of them, that ſaw their life in them, but bid all men to wait till their change come, and not to go forth by their own ſtrength, or awake their beloved before his time,
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.7.</note> till he ſhall come with a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199130:15"/>ſtrong hand, and lead them forth, and ſo place them in their own land, as in himſelf: And now having ſhewed them the vanity of all thoſe things, I then ſet before them the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, with exhortations to love one another, as a ſure teſtimony of their love to God; for the which I have been hated and perſecuted by ſome men of all opinions and religions whatſoever in the world, whether Papiſts, Prelates, Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Ranters, Quakers, and whatſoever opinion elſe below the truth; though I love them all, and am with them all, and they all with me but a cloud is over them, that they ſee me not, neither know me, that is, they ſee not my life, being not yet reconciled to it: yet when this cloud ſhall be taken away from all, and the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs riſen in all,
<note place="margin">Matth 23.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> then ſhall they ſee both me and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and have joy in each other, and be at peace with all men, as being all brethren of one family, ſons of one Father, heirs of one Kingdom, and ſo ſee themſelves and all men dwelling together in one City, or heaven [God.]</p>
               <p>And this is pure Religion, the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Kingdom of the Lord, and end of their journey; where <hi>the wolf ſhall dwell with the lamb</hi> (that is, the wicked with the godly, or men of all opinions meet and agree in one union and fellowſhip in the Lord Jeſus) <hi>And where the leopard ſhall lie down with the kid, and the calf, and the young lyon, and the fatlings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a little child</hi> (to wit Chriſt) <hi>ſhall lead them; and the cow and the bear ſhall feed</hi> (or all men who have been of different judgements, ſhall be of one mind in the Lord) <hi>their young ones ſhall lye down together</hi> (all men ſhall bring forth their ſeed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God) <hi>and the lyon ſhall eat ſtraw like the ox</hi> (or God will tame the wildeſt of creatures, the perſecutingſt: and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouringſt of men, or of things in men, that all ſhall be alike in knowledge) <hi>and the ſucking childe ſhall play on the hole of the aſp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and the weaned child ſhall put his hand on the cockatrice den</hi> (or he that is ſucking at the breaſt, and he that is weaned from the breaſt of his own Religion, and ſhall not one envy another) <hi>for the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the ſea:</hi> that is, God will ſo manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that all men and creatures ſhall be in union together,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199130:16"/>love one another, and do unto others, as they would others ſhould do unto them: this is the Law and the Prophets; and this is the Kingdom of the Lord, and high calling of God, which all men are to preſs after, and not to reſt till they are come in to it, and is no more nor no leſs then what I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways declared, as that which I received of the Lord; yet not that I <hi>Richard Coppin,</hi> as a creature, could at any time give to another what I my ſelf have received, or teach another what I am taught, or do for another what the Lord hath done for me in that caſe, but I onely declare what I have received of the Lord, and am taught by the Lord, and what the Lord may do for others, when the time appointed of the Father ſhall come; for he that gives to me, as a creature, muſt give to them as creatures;
<note place="margin">Iſa 2 22.</note> and he that taught me, muſt teach them, if ever they be taught the truth: therefore <hi>ceaſe from man, whoſe breath is in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> noſtrils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 2.</note> 
                  <hi>for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi> and eye him the Lord Jeſus, or that anointing within you, who is the ſalvation of all men, and whom you are to hear in all things; for all others beſides him, that go forth as Teachers of the people, are but falſe Teachers, and Seducers, according to the Scripture, but the Lord alone, or this anointing in us is our onely Teacher; and men in ſpeaking one to another, can do no more, as they are men, but tell one another what the Lord hath done for them; as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Come hear, and I will tell thee what the Lord hath done for my ſoul;</hi> and, <hi>what we have ſeen, and heard, we declare unto you,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul:</hi> which declarations of men may conform each other in ſomething which they before have had ſome little experience of in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Lord working with it, though they did not ſo know it as to utter it, which when it is declared to them, they may then ſet their ſeals to it as truth to them, there being in them the ſame ſpirit witneſſing to the ſame things, which makes them believe it; <hi>For he that believes hath the witneſs in himſelf;</hi> but if there be not the ſame ſpirit witneſſing in him that hears, as is in him that ſpeaks, they cannot believe, or ſet ſeal to the truth of what is ſpoken, any further then it agrees with their own ſpirits or opinions but will rather perſecute it to the death, and alſo them that ſhall declare it, as they have done to Chriſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199130:16"/>the Apoſtles, and others ſince; that from thence and from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch ariſes all perſecutions.</p>
               <p>And ſo having brought you thus far, to ſhew unto you my proceedings hitherto, both of my life and doctrine deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the world; I ſhall go on, and therein ſet before you a larger path of my perſecution and tryals, both at <hi>Worceſter, Oxford,</hi> and at <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> as of things conſiderable, from the firſt beginning to the end, as a further teſtimony to the truth: And firſt of my tryal at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and the proceedings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Miniſters malicious proceedings againſt the Author in Worceſterſhire, to bring him to a tryal: His examination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeveral Juſtices and Miniſters, and his being bound over to</hi> Worceſter <hi>Aſſizes; how, and for what.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe firſt proceedings of the Miniſters againſt me, to bring me to a tryal at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> was from my preaching at <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>load</hi> in Worceſterſhire, where I was deſired by ſome of the Eminenteſt men of that Pariſh to come, and there to preach, where I continued for the ſpace of four days, declaring the things which I had ſeen and heard of the Lord, both in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and private, with the deſire of the people, and the conſent of the ſaid Miniſter of that place: But the ſaid Miniſter finding the people ſo much adhering to what I delivered, and believing in it more then in what he himſelf uſually delivered amongſt them, he began to be wrath, and was troubled; and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he ſhould loſe his flock, or at leaſt the benefit he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of them, he ſent and cauſed a diſpute, or at leaſt a vain jangling to be between ſome certain Miniſters of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and my ſelf, while I was there; ſome of whoſe names are as follows, <hi>Eaſon</hi> of <hi>Batsford, Collier</hi> of <hi>Blackly, Nevil,</hi> and others, as Miniſters to the people in their ſeveral Pariſhes, but no grace could they miniſter to the hearers, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid in truth to be Miniſters of Chriſt but of Antichriſt, as appeared by what they declared to the people, as alſo by their practiſe; for they endeavoured to prove the Law under
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199130:17"/>that adminiſtration of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be ſtill in force, and that man by keeping of it, and doing the works thereof, ſhould be ſaved by it, and there would be no need of Chriſt (ſaid they) which thing I oppoſed them in, declaring ſtreightway to the people, that if it were by the works of the Law, by which no fleſh ſhould be juſtified, then not of grace: but being by grace, it is no more of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt, and ſay, they were fain to help God; and I further ſaid, that if it were poſſible for any man now to keep the Law in every part and point thereof; yet there were no ſalvation by it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God had found out another way, a new and a living way, even by Chriſt alone, or God manifeſt in fleſh; and to this Chriſt ſaith, that he was ſet up from everlaſting, to be the way, the truth and the light,
<note place="margin">Pro. 8.22, 23</note> and none can go to the father but by him: but the people hearing this, and therein confeſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſters, themſelves to be better ſatisfied in that which I had ſaid, then in what they had heard from them, the Miniſters left both me and the people, and went away raging againſt me, and ſaying, if they had me forth of the Church (that godly place) they would knock me on the head, or tread me underfoot: but I remained ſtill ſpeaking to the people, in which time they in this their rage went to <hi>Nevils</hi> houſe the Miniſter of that Town, and there conſulted what they might do to prevent my coming again into that Countrey; even as the Prieſts and Elders in the time of the Apoſtles did conſult together what they might do unto <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> to prevent the ſpreading of their doctrine among the people, whom they threatned and commanded, that they ſhould ſpeak no more in the name of Jeſus:
<note place="margin">Acts 4.</note> So thoſe Prieſts and Elders with whom I had to do, did in their conſultation agree to get a warrant from ſome Juſtice of Peace of that County againſt me, and in it to charge me with blaſphemy; and alſo threatned me with it, making it as publikely known as they could to fright me, though they knew not what blaſphemy was neither with what to charge me: but I hearing of it, and being willing to anſwer to any thing that I had ſpoke or done, I came to the ſaid Town, where I underſtood the warrant was; and I abiding at a friends houſe, ſent to the ſaid Miniſter of the ſame Town, to come and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199130:17"/>his warrant, which he reported he had againſt me; for I was not aſhamed to anſwer to any thing that they ſhould lay to my charge But before he came unto me, he went to the reſt of the ſaid Miniſters of that Countrey, to acquaint them with it, and to confer what they might do in it, I being come to Town, and they unſatisfied for the preſent what to have againſt me. But I willing to ſee the utmoſt of it, and it being ſo appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God that I ſhould, I tarried there all night, and the next morning came <hi>Nevil</hi> with the Officer, and ſerved the warrant upon me; which was, that I ſhould appear before the next Juſtice of Peace for that County, to anſwer for ſpeaking of blaſphemy; but my accuſers being not yet provided with things againſt me, they reported, as I was informed, that if I would forbear preaching after that manner, they would then forbear to trouble me; of which I took no notice, but was willing they ſhould proceed in the buſineſs, I being thereunto encouraged by the Lord; then they to have time to provide themſelves, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that no Juſtice ſhould meddle with it till we came to <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> which was from thence above twenty miles; whither I, with many friends I had in the ſame Town, then went; and there tarried till the next day before any accuſer came, or that any thing could be found againſt me; then to examine me they had called together ſeveral Juſtices, and many of the Clergy; and having nothing at preſent againſt me, they examined me upon a paper of Interrogatories, ſent in by the Prieſts my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers; which was, Whether I did not ſay ſuch things as they would there accuſe me of; they thereby endeavouring to catch ſomething from my own mouth at that time to accuſe me, having ſet ſeveral Watchmen over me (to wit Clergy men) for that purpoſe; but having nothing from thence againſt me, then <hi>Nevil,</hi> who before ſerved the warrant upon me, ſwore, that I ſhould ſay, That they were evil Angels (meaning the Miniſters, ſaid he) that brought the tidings of damnation, and ſuch ought not to be heard But they knowing themſelves to be ſuch that did declare ſuch things of terror to the people, and I ſo diſcovering of them, their malice was ſo great towards me that they would then have impriſoned me for ſo ſaying, and from the teſtimony of one man, my accuſer; but upon farther conſideration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199130:18"/>fearing they ſhould do more then they could anſwer, they paſſed that by, and bound me over to the Aſſizes, which was within four days after, there to anſwer to that, and what more they in the mean time could get witneſſes to ſwear; who alſo had appointed and imployed other Miniſters of their tribe in that County, to examine before ſome Juſtices, ſeveral perſons that had formerly been hearers of me, to ſee what more they could get againſt me from thence, but could not by them get any thing. Then the next Sabboth after my return from my examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and two days before the Aſſizes, I came again to <hi>Emload,</hi> the Town from whence I was accuſed; and I there being deſired, ſpoke ſomething among the people that day; then at night, I, with other friends, met together at one <hi>Thomas Rooks,</hi> in the ſame Town, where we diſcourſed upon the Scriptures; in which time came in ſome malicious perſons, as ſpies ſent (as was ſuppoſed) by the ſaid Miniſter of the place; who there propounded to me ſome queſtions, pretending for ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to be informed in their judgements: but it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they came to catch ſomething from me to witneſs againſt me at the Aſſizes, when they brought ſuch things againſt me as (they ſaid) I at that time ſpoke in private to them. And thus you may ſee of the wicked plots and devices of wicked men, to maintain their corrupt and ſelf-intereſts, and to keep up a rotten Kingdom that is periſhing and decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Who further proceeded againſt me as follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:199130:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of his tryal at</hi> Worceſter <hi>Aſſizes, before the Lord Chief Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> Wilde: <hi>The particular accuſations againſt him; and his anſwers to them, with the proceedings of the Court; and how.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>VPon the 23 day of <hi>March</hi> I appeared at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> at the general Aſſizes there holden for that County; where <hi>Ralph Nevil</hi> of <hi>Emload,</hi> and <hi>Giles Collier</hi> of <hi>Blockly,</hi> Miniſters of the ſaid places in the ſame County, preferred a Bill of Indictment againſt me to the Grand-Jury for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (as they ſaid) who ſo found it, and returned it into the Court, where my Lord Chief Barron <hi>Wilde</hi> ſate Judge of that Aſſize; before whom I was then called, and there made my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: then the Petty-Jury, and the witneſſes to the Bill being called, the Bill of Indictment was read in the Court; the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars whereof are as follows:</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="charges">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Charge in the Indictment.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FIrſt, that I ſhould ſay, That they were evil Angels (meaning the Miniſters who preach the Goſpel of Chriſt) that told peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of damnation, and that ſuch ought not to be heard or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly, That all men whatſoever ſhould be ſaved.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly, That thoſe that heard me were all in heaven, and in glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fourthly, That God was as much in them as in Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fifthly, That the Day of Judgement was begun</hi> 160 <hi>years ago.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sixthly, That there was no general Day of Judgement.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Seventhly, That there was no heaven but in man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fighthly, That he that thought there was abell, to him there
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199130:19"/>was a hell; but he that thought there was no hell, to him there was no bell.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And after the Indictment was read, my accuſers and the witneſſes to the Bill were ſworn, whoſe names are as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Ralph Nevil</hi> of <hi>Emload,</hi> and <hi>Giles Collier</hi> of <hi>Blockly,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers; <hi>William Petty, William Fletcher,</hi> and <hi>John Froobury</hi> of <hi>Emload</hi> witneſſes,
<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 26.60.</note> three in number, which was one more then Chriſt had; but never a couple of them ſwore one thing, but differed from each other in their Evidence, and who could hardly pronounce their words plain: but what they did ſwear, they had alſo in writing, what the pleaſure of my accuſers was to give them: and who were ready (as appeared) to ſwear any thing to accompliſh their own ends, two of them being ſons to one that rented the Glebe-land of <hi>Nevil,</hi> one of the accuſers, for whom they ſwore; and the other the Clerks ſon of the ſame Town. But this being done, I was called to my anſwer, and began with theſe Propoſitions, as follows:</p>
               <p>My Lord, I deſire your Lordſhip that you will be pleaſed to grant me theſe few particulars:</p>
               <p>Firſt, That my accuſers, being not men of the ſame diſcovery of God that I am, may therefore make it appear before this honourable Court, that they have taken the Ingagement, elſe they are not to have the benefit of the Law.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That no man whatſoever may be ſuffered to ſpeak any thing againſt me, till they are ſworn before this Honorable Court and my face.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That thoſe witneſſes which are here ready to teſtifie in my behalf, may be alſo heard, and theſe Certificates which are here brought after me by ſeveral men, with ſeveral mens names to them, may be alſo read.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That I may have time and liberty given me to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer fully to every particular that may at this time be laid to my charge; and having a fair tryal, I ſhall be thankful to your Lordſhip; all which particulars being granted, the Court proceeded.</p>
               <p>But before I came to anſwer their Indictment, my accuſers preſented to the Judge a book, with my name to it, entituled,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199130:19"/>
                  <hi>Mans Righteouſneſs Examined;</hi> which book the Judge asked me if I would own. I anſwered, that unleſs I heard it read, I knew not that it was mine. Then ſaid he, Here is your name to it. I anſwered again, that another might write a book, and put my name to it; or others of my name might write a book with that title: but if your Lordſhip will be pleaſed to cauſe the book to be read that I may hear it, I will tell you whether it be mine or no; who then read part of it himſelf, where he thought fit, and where my accuſers directed him. All which I anſwered, and owned to be mine, as it was read. Then ſaid the Judge, This book makes more for him then againſt him; for you accuſe him for denying heaven and hell, when he acknowledges both in his book; which book the Judge put in his pocket, and ſo came to the Indictment; to which my anſwer was more large then you will have it here.</p>
               <p>The firſt particular charged in the Indictment, and the anſwer to it was:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, that I ſhould ſay, That they were all evil Angels; meaning the Miniſters who preach the Goſpel of Chriſt</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>that told the people of damnation, and that ſuch ought not to be heard or believed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord, there are two adminiſtrations in manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; one of the Law, and another of the Goſpel: Firſt, that of the Law is a miniſtration of wrath, death, the curſe, hell and condemnation,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.</note> becauſe under it ſin appears to men unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Secondly, that of the Goſpel is a miniſtration of love, joy, peace, life, light, heaven, and ſalvation; for under that ſin appeared to men pardoned. And thoſe, who from Chriſt preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, bring tidings of good things, when they preach the love of God in Chriſt to all people, that they appear to be good meſſengers, and ſo good Angels, ſent of God; and ſuch ought to be heard and believed, as it is written,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> 
                  <hi>How beautiful are the feet of them that preach the Goſpel of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things? but though we or an angel from heaven preach any other Goſpel un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you then that which we have preached,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.1. &amp; 4.14.</note> 
                  <hi>let him be accurſed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) And you,</hi> ſaith he to the <hi>Galathians, received me as an Angel of God, even as Chriſt Jeſus, when I preached
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199130:20"/>unto you the Goſpel of Chriſt freely;</hi> when the other who preach up ſin unpardoned to any people after the coming of Chriſt, whoſe coming is to fulfil all righteouſneſs, and overcome all ſin for all people, are not Miniſters of the Goſpel, but of the Law, and ſo bring not tidings of good things, but of evil things; wherefore they appear to be evil meſſengers, and ſo evil angels, reſerved under chains of darkneſs ſo long; and ſuch men and doctrines ought not to be heard or believed, who believe not themſelves:
<note place="margin">John 14 1 &amp; 6 45. Acts 7.37</note> 
                  <hi>But hear and believe in me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>for you ſhall be all taught of me;</hi> and, <hi>Him ſhall you hear in all things,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo much of the anſwer to the firſt Article, to prove them evil angels, (even as devils) who preach up ſin unpardoned, and hold forth damnation belonging to any people any longer then while they believe not: and therefore I affirm, that ſuch ought not to be heard or believed, who themſelves believe not this to be true.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>That all men whatſoever ſhould be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam 14.14</note> God hath declared in Scripture both by the mouth of the Prophets and Apoſtles the ſalvation of all men, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons; who ſaith. <hi>He will have all men to be ſaved, and to come unto the knowledge of the truth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4, 5, 6, 7.</note> and, <hi>There is one Mediator between God and men, the man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelf a ranſom for all, to be teſtified in due time:</hi> And doth God will and deſire the ſalvation of all men? Then may we ſay, <hi>Lord, who hath reſiſted thy will?</hi> let <hi>thy will be done;</hi> as hath been our daily prayer unto him; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That as by one man death and damnation came to all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.18.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo by one life and ſalvation came to all;</hi> elſe Chriſt were not ſufficient to ſave all that <hi>Adam</hi> loſt, and to bring again all that was driven away: and it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſaid, that all men ſhall never be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth: but it is ſaid, that in due time all men ſhall be ſaved; and <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to preach this Goſpel to the world,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.32.</note> and to ſinners, yea all men whatſoever; and he ſaith, <hi>That God hath concluded them all under ſin and unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199130:20"/>
               <p>And now, <hi>If any man ſin, he hath an advocate with the Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 2, 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, who is a propitiation not onely for our ſins</hi> (or the ſins of a few, to wit,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.</note> Apoſtles and Saints) <hi>but alſo for the ſins of the whole world;</hi> and hath made full ſatisfaction for all, paid the debts of all, yea, all men paſt, preſent and to come, and that damnation to any creature is no longer but for that time wherein they believe not this to be done, as by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience I can teſtifie; <hi>for he that believes not is condemned already:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 3.16.</note> and a man may be an unbeliever one day, and a believer ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; therefore damned one day, and ſaved another: And that which all men are to be ſaved from,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2</note> and in due time ſhall be made manifeſt to them, is death and hell, in which abides the Devil, Sin and Damnation, all which ſhall be caſt into the lake of fire, there to be ended, that it no more ſhall riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them, to accuſe and condemn them: and God cannot, neither will he loſe any thing that is of himſelf, or is himſelf, but the ſon of perdition, that damnable ſtate of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, together with all that is of the creature as found out by the creature, to wit, his own invnetions, in that ſtate of ſin and death; for God made man upright, juſt and good; and I dare not ſay, that any creature which God made ſhall go to any local hell to be tormented, after he is departed out of this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble being, becauſe the Scripture ſaith it not, but ſaith, <hi>That the body when it falls, goeth to the earth from whence it came,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ 12.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and the ſoul to God that gave it:</hi> And it is moſt certain, that God gave to every man his ſoul; therefore he will take every mans ſoul to himſelf again, becauſe it can live in no other but him;
<note place="margin">Job. 12 10.</note> for every thing returns to its centre and ſtill lives and remains the ſame in and with God, as at the firſt, who will caſt away none that comes to him, and are of him; but one God made us all, and is a husband to us all, and we all are his Spouſe, though we all know it not; <hi>For thy maker is thy huſhand the Lord of hoaſts is his name, the God of the whole earth ſhall he be called;</hi> and though for the time of our rebellion againſt him, he may ſeem to us to hide his face from us (in our apprehenſions) yet with an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting loving kindneſs doth he ſtill love us, and will ſave us,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 54.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> and ſo cauſe us to behold his face again, to <hi>forget the ſhame of our youth, and the things that are behind, and remember the reproach
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199130:21"/>of our widowhood no more:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 54.4.</note> being now returned (in knowledge) to him who is our husband and firſt love, with whom we ſhall live for ever, world without end; therefore to ſay that all men whatſoever may be ſaved, though it appear not to them ſo long as they all believe not, is no more then what the Scripture ſaith. And ſo much of the anſwer to the ſecond Article, that all men whatſoever ſhould be ſaved.</p>
               <p>But my accuſers were troubled, and thought my anſwer too large, and the time too long that I had to plead; who told the Judge that my lungs were ſo ſtrong, that if he ſuffered me ſtill to go on, I would never have done; but the Judge honeſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them, ſaying, that he had heard them, and was now to hear me, who bid me go on.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>That all that heard me were in heaven and glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.27.</note> The Saints of God, which are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular, cannot be ſeparated from their head, which is Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.20.</note> being all members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones, and Chriſt the head of every man being in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in glory, every man therefore may be ſaid to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in glory with him; yea, in the ſame glory that Chriſt himſelf is in, though not yet revealed to them; for ſaith Chriſt to his Father, <hi>Father, glorifie me with thy ſelf, with the glory I had with thee before the world was; and the glory that thou haſt given me, I have given them, that they may be one, even as we are one,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 17.5.22, 23, 24, 25, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they be made perfect in one:</hi> And the deſire of Chriſt then was, that they might be with him to behold his glory; and, <hi>O righteous Father</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have declared unto them thy name, and will declare it, that the love wherewith thou haſt loved me may be in them, and I in them;</hi> And Chriſt and they being one in another, they cannot be parted one from another, but where the one is, the other is alſo; and Chriſt in raiſing up himſelf to heaven, raiſed up them with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.19. Iohn. 12.32.</note> for <hi>together with my dead body</hi> (or as my dead body) <hi>ſhall they ariſe</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and I, if I be lifted up, will draw all men unto me;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and, <hi>Both
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199130:21"/>he that ſanctifieth, and they who are ſanctified, are all of one</hi> (yea,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.6. Heb. 2.11.</note> of one God and Father) <hi>for which cauſe he is not aſhomed to call them brethren;</hi> and as they are all brethren, ſo they are alſo heirs, co-heirs, and joynt-heirs with him in the ſame heaven and glory of the Father, that Chriſt is heir in, though they yet know it not; and therefore all that is yet wanting in and to men, is onely a manifeſtation and enjoyment of this in themſelves, which in due time will be made manifeſt to them all, as the Lord Jeſus ſhall appear in them, and God by him be made known to them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>That God was as much in them as in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That God who is the power, life, and light of all men, and that cannot be divided from, neither confined to any one man, is the ſame in all men, as he was in that one man, called Chriſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> though he be not yet ſo fully manifeſted to and in all men,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> as he was to and in him, he being the firſt born among many bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or the firſt appearance of humane nature, in whom God did ſo fully and manifeſtly appear to be living, moving, acting, and bringing forth himſelf in the manifeſtation of his love in power, life, light and glory; yet that God is in all, and all are in him (as alſo ſaith the Scripture) <hi>for in him we all live, move,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 17.28. Epheſ. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and have our being;</hi> and, <hi>there is one God and Father of all, who is above all, through all, and in all,</hi> both in Jews, Gentiles, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, Pagans, Turks, Infidels, or whatſoever elſe they may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and there is no difference, or reſpect of perſons with God, but in the manifeſtation of this to themſelves, which none can have till the Holy Ghoſt, even the Spirit of truth, comes upon them, as it did on him, and reveal it to them, as it did to him, which he hath promiſed, that in due time ſhal come and bring all things to their remembrance: &amp; there is no man but hath God in him, yea, the ſame God that Chriſt had, though not the ſame meaſure of knowledge and underſtanding, till Chriſt in them hath revealed it. And that the Gentiles might come to know this, <hi>Paul</hi> prays for them, <hi>that they might be ſtrengthned with all might in the inner man</hi> (that is, with all God) <hi>to comprehend with all Saints what
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199130:22"/>is the bredth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>and length, and depth and heighth, and to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge, that they might be filled with all the fulneſs of God,</hi> even as Chriſt was, to have in them the ſame mind, the ſame love, life and light, and ſo be filled with the ſame fulneſs of grace and glory, whereby they come unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, to know that as he was, ſo are we in this world; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no blaſphemy to ſay that God may be as much in them as in Chriſt (conſidered as a man) though it do not yet appear ſo to them,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.13. 1 Ioh 4.17.</note> as in due time it may and will when God ſhall be more revealed to them, and they more enjoy him in the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>That the day of judgement was began ſixteen hundred years ago.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw</hi> My Lord, according to Scripture acceptation it was ſo;
<note place="margin">Iohn 12.13.</note> for ſaid Chriſt; <hi>Now is the Iudgement of this world; now ſhall the Prince of this world be caſt out;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 9 39.</note> 
                  <hi>and for Iudgement am I come into this world</hi> (ſaid Chriſt) <hi>that they which ſee not, might ſee; and that they which ſee might be made blind;</hi> and this coming of Chriſt to Judgement according to the Scripture, was above ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years paſt, and yet is continued to this day, though moſt men are blind and yet ſee it not, which ſome ſhall ſo long as they have eyes of their own to ſee, and ears of their own to hear, till they ſee with the Lords eye, and hear with the Lords ear; and the Apoſtle alſo ſaid, that the time was then come,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>that Iudgement muſt begin at the Houſe of God,</hi> even with righteous men, or men under any form of Religion, that had any thing of their own righteouſneſs to truſt in, beſides Chriſt their righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>That this day of Judgement did then begin, we find; for ſo ſoon as he was but aſcended and had led captivity captive, he ſent the holy Ghoſt the Comforter,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.7.8.</note> even the ſpirit of truth which ſhould convince the world of ſin, of righteouſneſs and of judgement; and ſo bring all things to mans remembrance, deſtroying all that is a lye in man by the ſpirit of Judgement and of burning; when he ſhall appear to ſit (in man his Temple)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:199130:22"/>as a refiner and purifyer of gold and ſilver,
<note place="margin">Mal 3.3.</note> to purge out all droſs, ſin and corruption, and to make man a veſſel holding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but righteouſneſs, peace and joy, which work of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was then begun with ſome, coming on to others, and is not ended to this day with all, neither will, ſo long as ſin is in the world raigning in any creature, and till we ſee ſin and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion finiſhed in us, as no more to be imputed to us;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.24. &amp;c.</note> we ſee not an end of the day of Judgement with us, till we ſee Chriſt to have opened the priſon doors, broken all bonds, put all enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet, ſet us at liberty, and delivered up the Kingdom to the Father, that God may be all in all; and ſo much for the day of Judgement, that it was began ſixteen hundred years ago, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Sixthly. <hi>That there was no general day of Iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord; I know no other day of Jodgement as to me, then what I have already declared to your Lordſhip, which is to be the ſame with every creature before it can be finiſhed; and this may be ſaid to be A general day, wherein all men are to appear before Chriſt to be Judged by him in love; for the time is come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though this time of Judgement may be called a day, yet this day may be thouſands of years before all the world in every man may be Judged, all ſin and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion finiſhed as to them, and they all ſet free in the Lord;
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>For one day with the Lord is as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day;</hi> and did men once taſte and feel of the workings of God in and upon their ſouls, in manifeſting his love to them, for the taking away of ſin and tranſgreſſion from them, they would then be ſatisfied touching this day of the Lord, which for my part I am already ſatisfied in, and therefore cannot but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, and bear witneſs to it as that which is truth to me, and according to the Scriptures; and they that know any other, let them declare that, as I have declared this.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:199130:23"/>
               <p>Seventhly. <hi>That there was no heaven but in man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord; Thoſe words do not ſay there is none at all, but that it is in man, yet without confinement, and this the Scripture alſo declares; therefore if we would know where heaven is, let us firſt know what it is, and the Scripture tells us, that the Kingdom of heaven is <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 14.17.</note> 
                  <hi>peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and that it is within us; for when the Scribes and Phariſes came to Chriſt to demand of him when the Kingdom of God ſhould come, (as men ſtill do) he anſwered them, that <hi>The Kingdom of God cometh not with obſervations, neither ſhall they ſay, lo here, or lo there; for behold the Kingdom of God is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you;</hi> and where ſhould the Kingdom of Chriſt, which is a Kingdom of righteouſneſs, peace and joy appear to be, that men might have peace and joy in it, and God glorified by it, but in man, the place which the Lord hath appointed for himſelf to dwell in? for behold the Tabernacle of God is with men, that he might be a Comforter to them, to encreaſe amongſt them righteouſneſs, peace, and joy, which is the Kingdom of the Lord; and till we have it in our ſelves, we have it not any where; but if there, then every where, which is a new name written that no man knows but he that hath it; and thus the Scripture declares unto us, what, and where heaven is, and I know no other heaven (as to me) in which is mans ſalvation, from ſin, death, hell, and the world, but Chriſt in man, and man in Chriſt; and they that will have any other, let them declare what and where that is, as I have declared what and where this is, which is according to the Scripture, and my own experience.</p>
               <p>Eighthly. <hi>That he who thought there was a hell, to him there was a hell; but he that thought there was no hell, to him there was no hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord, I yet know no other hell as to me, then what I have found in my own conſcience, though the time hath been, that I have feared another as moſt men do, and as all men elſe have done till their conſciences were purged: but this I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:199130:23"/>have found in my ſelf that when it pleaſed God to make know Chriſt to me, to take away from me the fear of hell, he alſo took away hell; <hi>for fear hath torment;</hi> therefore to me it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that while we live in the fear of hell, we have it, are in it, and ſo ſubject to the puniſhment of it, being kept in bondage by it, till Chriſt in us ſhall deſtroy that fear, and ſo ſet our minds at liberry, as is written, <hi>That for as much as the children are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of fleſh and blood, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf took part of the ſame, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, which is the Devil, and ſo free them who all their life time were ſubject to bondage;</hi> and now happy is that ſoul that ſees himſelf ſo made free by Chriſt; for he is free indeed, and now ſees an end of the Devil, ſin, death, and hell, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lived in fear of, and was in bondage to; and therefore when the Lord Jeſus is pleaſed to deliver us from the fear of it, that it ſhall no more have power over us, and thereby manifeſt in us perfect love wherein is no fear, he then delivers us from hell it ſelf, from which every believer is freed;
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>but the fearful and unbelieving, and the abominable and murthehers, and whoremong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſorcerers, and Idolaters, and all lyars,</hi> (while they ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main) <hi>are caſt into it,</hi> and ſo have their part in the Lake of fire burning with brimſtone, till the Lord Jeſus by his mighty power ſhall quench the fire, raiſe them up, and overcome all their enemies for them, and ſo reſtore peace to them, in him that is their peace, the Lord Jeſus; and then he that hath part in the firſt reſurrection through Chriſt (or is once made free by Chriſt) of him the ſecond death ſhall have no power; but he is changed from death unto life by the ſpirit of the Lord, and ſo ſees an end of death and hell, as to him: All which I ſhall leave to your Lordſhips conſideration and this honourable Court, and do give you many thanks for that I have had liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſpeak for my ſelf.</p>
               <p>But my accuſers were much troubled that I had ſo fair a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and began to urge many other things of their own inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt me, which was not in the Indictment. Firſt they ſaid, that I denyed the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in ſaying there was no ſalvation by it, which they affirmed it was if man would keep it; That if it were poſſible for a man now to keep the Law in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199130:24"/>letter of it (which that it is impoſſible) yet there would be no ſalvation by it for any man: God having found out another way, even by Jeſus Chriſt, without which no man could be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They ſaid, that I denyed the keeping of the Sabboth, which they went to prove from the fourth Commandment, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou keep holy the Sabboth day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwered, that the true Sabboth of a Chriſtian was Chriſt, and I knew no other, as to me, though that day which they now call a Sabboth day, I keep it as exactly and as purely as any of them did, in preaching to the people; but not upon the account of a Sabboth day, but as the firſt day of the week, as the Apoſtles did, being a day ſet apart for that uſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They ſaid, that I ſpake in deriſion of heaven, ſaying that if a Mill-ſtone were at heaven, it would be hundreds of years a coming down.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwered, That I never ſaid the words, but one in my company did once ſay, that they were ſpoken by a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Pulpit, who there endeavouring to ſhew unto the people the vaſt diſtance between heaven and earth; told them, that if a Mill-ſtone were at heaven, it would be many hundred years a coming down, and that one of his hearers ſhould make anſwer, that if heaven were above the skies, and a Mill-ſtone ſo long a coming down, how long then ſhould he be a going up? And this, my Lord, was declared by one of their own tribe, yet they would aſcribe it to me, though I never ſaid the words.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They ſaid, that I ſhould deny the reſurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſaid, there was no other but what was in flowers and graſs; alſo when the Corps laid in a grave were caſt up again, though turned to earth, then was there a reſurrection.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwered, that the reſurrection of the dead I never denyed, but do alwayes affirm it; neither did I ever ſpeak thoſe words, though they might be ſpoke in my company: Yet it may be ſaid that in this there is a reſurrection, though not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying any other, for the vertue of every carkaſs laid in the earth, doth aſcend upwards with the earth, and ſo come forth in flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and graſs; alſo when a grave is digged, and the body before
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:199130:24"/>laid in it, though rotted to earth, again caſt up with the bones and all things thereto belonging, then may it be ſaid to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of that body, and the true reſurrection not denyed: but thoſe things being thus anſwered, and the malice of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers made manifeſt, the Judge appeared more ſatisfied, and my accuſers more aſhamed.</p>
               <p>Then after the Judge had heard the whole buſineſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the ſubſtance thereof to the Jury (who underſtood it not) they went forth to conſult upon their Verdict, whether all, or any part of the charge were blaſphemy by the Act, or no; who returned in their Verdict, guilty: being asked of what part, they ſaid of that concerning heaven and hell.</p>
               <p>Then the Judge told them, that unleſs it came directly under the Act of blaſphemy in every particular point, it could not be found as blaſphemy; who himſelf call'd for the Act, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it with the Indictment, found it not as the Jury had ſaid, to be within the Act for blaſphemy, for which he reproved them, repeating the words of the Act to them, which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judge.</hi> He that ſhall avowedly affirm and maintain there is no heaven and hell, its blaſphemy by that Act, but that he doth not ſay but doth acknowledge there is a heaven and hell in man, as you ſee him prove, and therefore doth not affirm there is none at all: and words ſpoken by way of private conference in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, (as the witneſſes do confeſs this was) it might be only ſpoken by way of Propoſition or Querie, to try the Judgements of others, and not as his own judgement; and then cannot be ſaid to be avowed and affirmed, therefore not within the Act: however he ſhall continue bound till the next Aſſizes, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Law, as ſaid the Judge.</p>
               <p>Then I deſired liberty to ſpeak a little more before I departed from the Court: which was as follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:199130:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Speech made to the Judge after the Tryal, to vindicate his own and other mens preaching, without a call from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; wherein is a true diſcovery of the word of God and the Scripture, what it is. Of his taking his leave of the Court.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>MY Lord, I have here been maliciouſly and falſly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by my adverſaries, as hath appeared before the Court this day; and now is the law open on my behalf againſt all that have falſly appeared againſt me; but he that is my Teacher teaches me no ſuch thing, as to ſeek revenge; but free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to forgive my enemies, to love them that hate me and ſo leave all things to him, who will reward every man according to his works; <hi>For vengeance is mine, and I will repay</hi> (ſaith the Lord.)</p>
               <p>And the reaſon why thoſe men do thus perſecute me, is for the malice they have againſt me for exerciſing theſe gifts that God hath given me for his glory, the comfort of my ſoul, and benefit of his people; which gifts they know not, becauſe they know not him, neither will they hear him, but ſpeak evil of the things that are taught by him; when without him we know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27.</note> and are taught nothing, according as it is written, <hi>That no man knows the Son, but the Father; nor no man knows the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the Son, and he to whom the Son ſhall reveal him:</hi> So the true knowledge of God is not taught of man,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1 12.15, 16.</note> nor by men, but comes onely by the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, as that which is moſt hated by men: And when it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in me, as he did in <hi>Paul,</hi> I, with him, conferred not with fleſh and blood, as thoſe men do; that is, I went not to this or that place, as unto men, to receive orders from them, and to know before hand what I ſhould have for my preaching, as other men do, and have done; but I went immediately declaring the things I had ſeen and heard from the Lord, whereſoever I was deſired; and what I did, was freely, and in love to the Lord Jeſus and his people, without any price or reward of men; when others who have their gifts from men, will look to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199130:25"/>by men; and good reaſon too that men ſhould ſell what they buy: But thoſe mens gifts are bought, therefore do they ſell them, as other Tradeſ-men do, for their own advantage; for if they can have but five or ten pound more in another Pariſh, they will leave the one for the other, and yet no longer then they pay them, will they preach to them, without going to Law with them; which ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ws that they preach not in love to the Lord Jeſus and his people, but in love to that which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have, and ſo ſeek not them, but theirs; when I for my part in all my practice of preaching hitherto, have not ſought theirs, but them,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.14, 15.</note> and would gladly ſpend and be ſpent for them to do them good, as they will be ready to teſtifie: And for this am I hated and perſecuted by them that know me not; nevertheleſs I cannot but ſpeak the things that I have been taught of the Lord; <hi>for as every man hath received the gift, ſo let them admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter one to another;</hi> and, <hi>What is revealed an ſecret, ſhall be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed upon the houſe tops</hi> (ſaith the Lord) and this ſhall I do if God permit.</p>
               <p>The Judge ſaid, And you do well in ſo doing; for you may preach whereſoever you are deſired, ſo long as you keep cloſe to the word of God, and make that to be your rule.</p>
               <p>I anſwered, my Lord, I thank you, and I ſhall do ſo. But what do you call the Word of God?</p>
               <p>Said the Judge, the Scripture is the Word of God.</p>
               <p>I anſwered, that the Scripture, as written in ink and paper, is not the Word of God, but a dead letter, which in the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hearing thereof, tells us onely in the ear what the Word of God is, but cannot teach or tell the mind; neither doth it any where ſay for it ſelf, that it ſelf is the Word of God that can teach us; but that we are all taught of the Lord, who is himſelf the Word, the Unction, the Holy one, and anointing within us; therefore let us not give more honour to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture then the Scripture takes to it ſelf, but let honour be given to whom honour is due, and glory to whom glory is due; and in this we ſhall give all unto God, who is himſelf the true Word and Teacher, as the Scripture declares him to be; for ſaith <hi>John, In the beginning was the Word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Word was with God, and the word was God; the ſame was in the beginning with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:199130:26"/>God:</hi> and this Word became fleſh and dwelt among us, that it might teach us all things (and ſaith <hi>John</hi>) <hi>we behold the glory of him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 14.</note> 
                  <hi>as the glory of the onely begotten Son of God, full of grace and truth,</hi> which is not the Scripture, as written in the Letter, but God written in our fleſh, is this Word.</p>
               <p>Again ſecondly, the Scripture tells us, that <hi>the word of God is quick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and powerful, &amp; ſharper then any two-edged ſword peircing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart:</hi> And this the Scripture cannot do, but God himſelf, as the Scripture tells us; for it ſaith, That he is the ſearcher of the heart, and the tryer of the reins, and the divider aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and diſcerns the thoughts and intents of mens hearts; and ſo the ſearcher and tryer of all things (as ſaith the Scripture.)</p>
               <p>Again thirdly, the Scripture tells us of Chriſts riding upon a white horſe, conquering and to conquer, and that his name was called <hi>The Word of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 19, 11, 12, 13.</note> and not that the Scriptures were ſo called: And let not us rob God of that honour and title due unto himſelf, to give to the Scripture, but what the Scripture ſaith both of God and it ſelf, that let us ſay alſo. The Scripture alſo ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6. Iohn 14.19. Rom 10.8.</note> that <hi>the Letter kills, but the Spirit gives life;</hi> which ſpirit is the Word, and the Word is Chriſt. <hi>I am come that you may have life</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) and, <hi>becauſe I live, ye ſhall live al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo:</hi> And this Word (even Chriſt) is nigh us, in us, yea round about us, ſtill teaching of us, and giving life unto us, which is the work of Chriſt, and not the Scripture. But this I will ſay of the Scripture (which is what the Scripture ſaith of it ſelf) that it is an outward teſtimony of God, his mind, Chriſt the Word, Faith and Eternal Life, Heaven and Salvation to thoſe that do believe; but not that it ſelf is either of all theſe, or can give unto us the knowledge of it; and that we might know the inſufficiency of it,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.39.40</note> Chriſt in it bids us <hi>ſearch the Scriptures</hi> (for ſaith he) <hi>in them you think to have eternal life, and they are they which teſtifie of me; and ye will not come to me, that ye may have life:</hi> Yet this Scripture, as it is given by inſpiration, ſo it is profitable for doctrine,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> for reproof, for correction and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in righteouſneſs, that the man of God may be perfect,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:199130:26"/>throughly furniſhed to all good works: and not as it lies in the letter, but as it is inſpired, revealed or made manifeſt in our hearts and minds by the Holy Ghoſt: for (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I will put my law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 31.33, 34.</note> 
                  <hi>and cauſe them to walk in my ſtatutes,</hi> of loving one another.</p>
               <p>And the Word of God being once written in our hearts, it is then profitable for us, to teach reprove, correct and inſtruct us, make us perfect in the inward man, furniſh us, fit and qualifie us with gifts and graces unto all good works, and no otherwiſe can it do it for us, but as it is within us.</p>
               <p>And this is the honour and praiſe that I will give to the Word of God, and to the Scripture, to ſum it all up in God, in whom I deſire to know, to live, to act, and enjoy all things of God; and I deſire not to ſpeak, think, act or maintain any thing that I have not the letter for, as well as the Spirit; the truth and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of which letter no man knows till he hath it revealed to him by the Spirit, and Internal Word, that declares the Father plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which ſo far as it ſpeaks in me,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27.</note> and declares the mind of God to me, I ſhall not be ſilent.</p>
               <p>And now, my Lord, I give you many thanks that you have ſo patiently heard me, and given me liberty to ſpeak for my ſelf. Yet before I depart, I ſhall deſire to preſent one Scripture more, which I ſhall but onely read, and ſo leave it to the conſideration of this honourable Court.</p>
               <p>Said the Judge, I thought you had done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If your Lordſhip deſire it, I have.</p>
               <p>Said the Judge, Nay, but we will hear your Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is in the ſixth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> from the 8. verſe to the end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And Steven full of faith and power, did great wonders and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles among the people: then there aroſe certain of the Synagogue, which is called the Synagogue of the Libertines, Cyreneans, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drians, and of them of Cilicia, and of Aſia, diſputing with Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and they were not able to reſiſt the wiſdom and the ſpirit by which he ſpake; then they ſuborned men, which ſaid, we have heard him ſpeak blaſphemous words againſt Moſes, and againſt God; and they ſtirred up the people, and the Elders, and the Scribes, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:199130:27"/>came upon him, and caught him, and brought him to the Councel, and ſet up falſe witneſſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>which ſaid, This man ceaſeth not to ſpeak blaſphemous words againſt this holy place, and the Law; for we have heard him ſay, that this Jeſus of Nazareth ſhall deſtroy this place, and ſhall change the Cuſtoms which Moſes delivered us: and all that ſate in the Counſel, looked ſtedfaſtly on him, ſaw his face as it had been the face of an Angel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I ſhall take my leave, according as the Apoſtles in times paſt have done, who when they had ſuffered for the name of Chriſt, they <hi>departed from the preſence of the Council, rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his name</hi> (ſo ſhall I at this time) <hi>and</hi> (as) <hi>daily in the temple, and in every houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 5.41, 42.</note> 
                  <hi>they ceaſed not to teach and preach Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo ſhall not I, my Lord, ceaſe to do the ſame, ſo far as God ſhall enable me; and ſo I take my leave of your Lordſhip.</p>
               <p>And paying the fees of the Court, I was diſcharged for that time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors ſecond appearing at</hi> Worceſter, <hi>before Judge</hi> Nicholes <hi>and the proceedings thereof: alſo his being bound from thence to</hi> Oxford; <hi>how, and for what.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ANd I ſtanding bound until the next Aſſizes at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which was then ſix moneths to come, my accuſers <hi>Ralph Nevil</hi> and <hi>Giles Collier</hi> in the mean time imployed men on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to follow me from place to place, where they heard I preached or came, to enquire into my Doctrine, Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, with endeavours to get ſomething more againſt me, to accuſe me at the next Aſſizes following, as my ſelf and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons well knew. And they hearing of ſome difference in diſpute that was between ſome Miniſters and my ſelf at <hi>Enſtone</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> where I had before been and preached, they came to an Inn in <hi>Enſton,</hi> and ſent for the Miniſters that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:199130:27"/>differed with me, of whom they got a certificate of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars which they ſaid I there delivered, and which they counted blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>And when I appeared at <hi>Worceſter</hi> next Aſſizes, before Judge <hi>Nicholes,</hi> my accuſers gave to the Judge their certificate, which was as follows: Firſt, <hi>That I ſhould ſay Chriſt ayed for his own ſins as well as the Peoples.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That there was no heaven and hell but what was in man.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That everlaſting life ſhould end in this life.</hi> But no witneſs ſworn to it: And my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers having no witneſs there, they, with many fair ſpeeches uſed to the Judge deſired him to bind me to appear at the next General Aſſizes holden at <hi>Oxford,</hi> to anſwer to what was in this their certificate, and what more they in the mean time could find againſt me: For, ſaid they to the Judge, that being his own Countrey, we ſhall there by that time get ſomething more againſt him. And the Judge willing to do my accuſers a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt me, as <hi>Feſtus</hi> did the Jews againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> when he left him bound: So Judge <hi>Nicholes,</hi> without any oath made by any man againſt me, demanded of me bail for my appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at <hi>Oxford</hi> Aſſizes which was ſix moneths after that, and would not ſuffer me to ſpeak for my ſelf, but took part with my accuſers.</p>
               <p>Then I deſired of him law and juſtice; and told him, that there being nothing upon oath proved againſt me, there was no reaſon that I ſhould ſtand any longer bound</p>
               <p>Said the Judge, if I will have it ſo, you ſhall ſtand bound, &amp;c</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord, if you will make your will a Law. I cannot help that; but this I know that as you uſe the exactneſs of the Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n condemning thoſe whom the Law condemns, ſo you ought to uſe the exactneſs of the Law, in freeing thoſe whom the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw frees. But the Law at this time frees me, therefore I deſire it.</p>
               <p>No, ſaid the Judge, you ſhall not be freed, for I underſtand that you take upon you to preach and never ſtayed to take your degrees at the Univerſity; you ſhall therefore appear at <hi>Oxford</hi> to anſwer to thoſe things there. And ſaid the Judge, if I would take upon me to preach, I could preach as well as you,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:199130:28"/>and better, for I was bred up to more learning then you, and yet I wil not take it upon me, becauſe I was not called to it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> My Lord, I was called to Preach, and you were not; do you know what the call is? if you did, you would not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it; and if it be the Lords will that I muſt appear at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> to anſwer things as I have done at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> his will be done; for I remember what the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Paul</hi> when he was bound from place to place;
<note place="margin">Act. 23.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Be of good cheer</hi> Paul (ſaid he) <hi>for as thou haſt teſtified of me in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſo muſt thou bear witneſs alſo at</hi> Rome; and now am I not only ready to be bound, but to ſuffer for his name, and to bear witneſs of the Truth at <hi>Oxford,</hi> as I have done at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and ſhall have peace in all things therein, knowing it to be the Lords cauſe for which I ſtand bound. So giving in bayl, and paying the Fees of the Court, I was diſmiſſed until the next appearance at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors tryal at</hi> Oxford <hi>Aſsizes before Serjeant</hi> Green, <hi>the particular accuſations againſt him, and his anſwers to them, with the proceedings of the Court, and how; alſo the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Jury, and the malice of his Adverſaries diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>VPon the tenth day of <hi>March</hi> 1652. I appeared at <hi>Oxford</hi> Aſſizes, where <hi>Ralph Nevil</hi> of <hi>Emload,</hi> and <hi>Giles Collier</hi> of <hi>Blockly</hi> in the County of <hi>Worceſter</hi> preferred a Bill of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment againſt me to the Grand Jury (as they ſaid) for blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; the Charge therein is as follows.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:199130:28"/>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Charge in the Indictment.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt. <hi>(That I ſhould ſay) That Chriſt dyed for his own ſins at well as the Peoples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly. <hi>That there is no heaven and hell but what is in man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly. <hi>That everlaſting life ſhould end in this life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe are the things which by them I was Indicted for as blaſphemy, and which by the Grand Jury were ſo found and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Court, that I was put upon the tryal thereof.</p>
                  <p>But before you come to the tryal, I ſhall ſpeak ſomething of both Juries, as of carnal natural men, and ſo ignorant of ſuch things as they were to enquire into concerning me; for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man knows not the things of God, neither can he, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned: but ſure for the moſt part they were but carnal men, therefore in ſuch things ignorant men, and againſt ſuch things malitious men, as hath been known: being alſo men for the moſt part known to be of the Biſhops and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian opinion, very few of the Independents, though there is but little difference between them in their opinions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their judgements and knowledge in ſuch things, of whom it may be ſaid and alſo proved, as hath appeared by their practiſe, that they aim more at their own worldly, private, and ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, then at the glory of God, or good of other people, and which is well known have been, and gladly would be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of thoſe that live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, and that are not the ſame with them in their opinions, as hath appeared by ſome of them, which both I and others have already known by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: yet I love them ſtill in the ſame love as I love all others, and will the ſalvation of their ſouls as of all others, though they may not ſo love me, but hate me, for that they never ſaw or heard from me.</p>
                  <p>And therefore it is moſt evident, that they proceeded againſt me from the malice they had to me, and not any thing known by me for any blaſphemy there was in it, for I am ſure there was
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:199130:29"/>none, neither could any be found, either by the Law of God or of man as firſt for the Law of God I am ſure it is not, for there is nothing in all the Scripture writ againſt it; however all blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy on Gods part is forgiven, and Chriſt hath already an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered for it, in the behalf of all men.</p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, for the Law of man or any late Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament made againſt blaſphemy, I am alſo ſure that there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a particular contained in this Bill that comes within the compaſs of the Act: as for the firſt and laſt particulars in the Bill, that Chriſt ſhould die for his own ſins, as well as for the peoples, and that everlaſting life ſhould end in this life, there is no mention of it made in the Act. Then for the ſecond, that there is no heaven and hell but what is in man, there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of it neither, as theſe words are laid down and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Bill; for the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſaith, If any ſhall avow and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that there is no heaven and hell then it is blaſphemy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Act, but in this Bill, or in theſe words before mentioned, there is a heaven and a hell acknowledged, though not ſuch a one as ſome men would have, but ſuch a one as is in man, which is according to the Scripture, and ſome mens expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; yet not that any other is denyed, which by others may be proved, and there being (in the Bill) a heaven and a hell ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged it therefore comes not within the compaſs of the Act, and then cannot be found guilty by the Act.</p>
                  <p>Again, the witneſſes to the Bill do confeſs that theſe words fell in by way of diſpute or conference after Sermon, and were not ſpoke in Sermon, therefore cannot be ſaid to be avowed and affirmed, as the Judge did very well make it appear in the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: and which if the honeſt behaviour of the Juries had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo far, they, before they had condemned it, ſhould have examined whether the words in the Bill did reach any Act of Parliament or no, that made it appear to be what in the Bill it was ſaid to be, without which they ought not to have found it, though the Bill ſo ſaid it; for let any Bill ſay what it will, they are to examine it whether it be what in the Bill it is ſaid to be or no, as treaſon, blaſphemy, felony, or whatſoever crime elſe in the Bill may be expreſt, without which they are not to find any Bill, and for want of this, many a man and cauſe have ſuffered;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:199130:29"/>and now how honeſt and juſt his Jury have been in the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this Bill, according to Law and Juſtice, when they found it, and brought guilty; let all men that read and hear it, Judge of it; but ſo much for both the Juries; next the tryal in the Court.</p>
                  <p>And then the Bill being read, the witneſſes to the Bill were called to give in their evidence, whoſe names are as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, one <hi>Beckingam</hi> of <hi>Enſton</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> the Miniſter of the Pariſh where theſe words for which I am accuſed were (as they ſay) ſpoke, and that gave me leave to preach in his ſaid Pariſh Church the whole day, but afterwards finding the people to be more taken with my Doctrine (which was the Doctrine of free grace) then with his (that was not) and fearing his own ſhould be no more ſo well accepted, he cryes out againſt mine as blaſphemy, and ſo comes to witneſs againſt me for it, who to excuſe himſelf, ſaid he came not as an accuſer, but was brought only as a witneſs, whoſe teſtimony was according to the Bill.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond witneſs was one <hi>Cannon</hi> of the ſame Town, a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the ſaid <hi>Beckingam,</hi> who at that preſent approved very well of what I had ſaid, as himſelf afterwards confeſſed to ſome others, and ſaid it was the beſt Sermon that ever he heard in his life, till his Maſter the ſaid Miniſter of the Pariſh had tutoured him and made him change his opinion, who then came as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alſo, and whoſe conſcience began to accuſe him when he was to give in his teſtimony (as it there appeared) for when he ſhould have ſaid life everlaſting ended in this life, he could not for his life bring forth the word everlaſting but ſaid that this life ended in this life; and when the Judge asked him again, he ſaid, that when a man dyed his life ended but could not ſay the word everlaſting, till he had it given him in writing by my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers <hi>Nevil</hi> of <hi>Emload,</hi> and <hi>Collier</hi> of <hi>Blockly,</hi> two conſtant accuſers of the brethren, and that had been my accuſers before at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> as before was declared; who never heard thoſe things delivered by me at <hi>Enſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> which they accuſed me for: neither me, when I preached there though they here became my accuſers, and did alſo plead theſe things againſt me at <hi>Oxford:</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:199130:30"/>firſt to the Grand Jury, and after to the Court, alſo laying ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things to my charge which I knew not: but I believe it was with an intent to make good what they had before ſaid, which was, that they would not leave me till they had my life, which was the ſame that the Jews ſaid of <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 23. ver. 12.29.</note> who made a vow that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed <hi>Paul;</hi> but they were prevented, as theſe my accuſers have been hitherto concerning me. And <hi>Paul</hi> being accuſed of queſtions of their Law,
<note place="margin">Acts 26.31, 32.</note> as I now was, they kept him faſt bound ſtill for many years, and examined him before many counſels, but in the end nothing being found againſt him worthy of death or of bonds, and his accuſers being weary of proſecuting, he was then freed and ſet at liberty.</p>
                  <p>And the evidence being given, I was called to my anſwer, which begins with theſe Propoſitions, as follows.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>HAving here liberty to anſwer for my ſelf, I therefore hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech your Lordſhip to grant me theſe particulars.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Firſt.</hi> That ſeeing theſe my Adverſaries are men of a contrary diſcovery of God; and are here come againſt me, that they may fairly make it appear before this honourable Court, whether they are men that have taken the ingagement or no, without which I know them not to have the benefit of the Law, and I ſpeak it for this reaſon (my Lord) becauſe they being Miniſters of Pariſhes, and I knowing ſome of them not to obſerve the laſt thankſgiving day, with many others before, which by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was appointed to be kept, makes me to queſtion this thing.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly.</hi> That none might be ſuffered to ſpeak any thing againſt me in this honourable Court, till ſuch time that they are ſworn before this Court and my face.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly.</hi> That thoſe men which were hearers of me at <hi>Enſton</hi> (the time when tis ſaid theſe words were delivered, and are here preſent) may be ſuffered to ſpeak; alſo a certificate which I underſtand is by them brought, touching the things of my charge, and of my Doctrine then delivered, with another from <hi>Oxford,</hi> and ſeveral mens names to them both, who are here
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:199130:30"/>ready to teſtifie the truth of them, that they alſo may be read in this Honourable Court, for the ſatisfaction of many people; and thereby ſhew the miſtakes of my adverſaries, in the things which they accuſe me.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fourthly.</hi> That I may have liberty to ſpeak for my ſelf, in anſwer to every particular accuſation in my charge brought againſt me. And theſe things being granted, I ſhall be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to your Lordſhip.</p>
                        <p>Said the Judge, what you deſire ſhall be granted, and you ſhall have a fair tryal, but we ſhall not hear any Certificates read.</p>
                        <p>But the time being ſhort, the night coming on, and I haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called to anſwer to my charge, being my ſelf willing alſo to come to it, fearing I ſhould be ſtreightned in time, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubting of my coming off, that ſome of thoſe things which were by me deſired before to be granted, were paſſed by, and no more remembred; and theſe Certificates before mentioned, being not then permitted by the Judge to be read in the Court, it was therefore deſired by thoſe that ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, to have them printed with the reſt, to ſhew unto the world what it was they ſet their hands unto; ſome having ſince charg'd them with ſetting their hands to vindicate blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: which Certificates are as follow.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>A Copy of a Certificate preſented to the Court, by many of the godly and well-affected people living about <hi>Enſton,</hi> in the behalf of <hi>Richard Coppin.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE whoſe names are here under-written, were all at the hearing of <hi>Richard Coppin,</hi> the time when he preached at <hi>Enſton,</hi> and heard all that was then delivered; yet heard not any thing delivered by him, but what was truth, according to the Scripture and our experience, in which we were ſatisfied, and ſhould be glad to imbrace the like opportunity, as to hear the like again, if providence ſhould ſo order it.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:199130:31"/>
                  <p>And whereas (through the miſtake of ſome men in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions) he is or may be accuſed for any thing then deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: As,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, for ſaying <hi>That Chriſt ſhould ſuffer for his own ſins as well as the Peoples.</hi> We do hereby teſtifie that he at that time did again and again ſay, that Chriſt ſuffered not for them as acted by him, but as imputed to him, and ſo they became his which he proved from theſe Scriptures, <hi>He was made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> for us;</hi> and, <hi>The Lord hath laid upon him the iniquity of us all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Secondly, That he ſhould ſay, <hi>There is no heaven and hell but what is in man.</hi> He did not but did prove from Scripture, that there was a heaven and a hell in man, not denying any other, which by others might be believed, as to them.</p>
                  <p>And Thirdly, That he ſhould ſay, <hi>That everlaſting life ſhould end in this life.</hi> He did not; but ſaid, That there was that writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Scripture, which was ſaid to be everlaſting, yet had an end; as he proved from the ending of the firſt Covenant and Prieſt-hood under the Law, with the conditions thereof, which was ſaid to be for ever.</p>
                  <p>And Fourthly, as to his life and converſation, it hath been ſo civil, honeſt and reſpective towards all men, for all that ever we ſaw or knew of him that none ever yet could accuſe him; and therefore we do believe, that for the good that is in him and proceeds from him, to the edifying of many people, he is hated and perſecuted. To all which particulars, we have here ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed our names, and ſhall be ready to take our Oaths.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:199130:31"/>
                  <head>A Copy of a Certificate preſented to the Court by many of the godly and well-affected people of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the behalf of <hi>Richard Coppin.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE the Inhabitants of the City of <hi>Oxford,</hi> whoſe names are here underwritten, do hereby certifie, That <hi>Richard Coppin</hi> hath ſeveral times preached in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and hath been heard by us; who never heard any thing delivered by him, to our knowledge, but what hath been true and ſound doctrine, according to the Scripture, and the manifeſtation of God to us: And we do alſo certifie, that his life and converſation hath ever been towards all ſorts of men, honeſt, juſt and upright, that ever we could ſee, know, or hear of him. Concerning which, we have here ſubſcribed our names, and ſhall be alſo ready to teſtifie upon Oath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The firſt particular Charged in the Indictment.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, <hi>That I ſhould ſay, That Chriſt Jeſus the Son of God, and Saviour of the world, did ſuffer for his own ſins as well as the Peoples.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord, for anſwer to this, I do affirm, and ever did ſince I knew and declared any thing of God, That Jeſus Chriſt the Son of the living God, and Saviour of the whole world, as he lives in God, never acted ſin, but imputatively all our ſins became his, were laid upon him,
<note place="margin">John 3.17. 1 John 2.2. Heb. 10.5, 6.7. Rom. 8.3. Heb. 2.14. Luke 1.74.</note> and reckoned to him by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and Jeſus Chriſt, as the Son, in obedience to the Father, freely took them upon himſelf, clothed himſelf with our fleſh, ſinful fleſh, and ſo ſuffered for ſin, overcame and condemned ſin, and all enemies in our nature; wherein his appearance in us, doth manifeſt to us, that he ſatisfied the Fathers juſtice, payed our ſcore, and ſet us at liberty; though Chriſt himſelf
<pb facs="tcp:199130:32"/>(which is,
<note place="margin">Mat. 1.23. 1 Pet. 2.22. 2 Cor 5.21. Iſa. 53. Rom. 5.10. Iohn 14.19</note> 
                     <hi>Emmanuel, God with us</hi>) <hi>did no ſin, neither was guil found in his mouth</hi> (as ſaith the Scripture) <hi>yet he was made ſin for us;</hi> and, <hi>The Lord hath laid upon him the iniquity of us all, and by his ſtripes are we healed:</hi> by his life are we ſaved and do live; for (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>Becauſe I live, ye ſhall live alſo:</hi> And now the head cannot be ſaid to live without the body, nor the body without the head;
<note place="margin">1 Cor 11.3. Epheſ. 5.23, 29, 30. Heb. 5.3. &amp; 7.27. 1 Cor. 12.12, 13, 27.</note> ſo not Chriſt without us, nor we without Chriſt, he being our head, and we members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones: and Chriſt ſuffering for the ſin of us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>his members) may alſo be ſaid to ſuffer for the ſin of his own body, whoſe body we are: for (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>Ye are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular;</hi> and in this ſenſe he may be ſaid to ſuffer for his own ſins, which is no blaſphemy to ſay.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>That there is no heaven and hell but what is in man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord, for anſwer to this, I do affirm, and ever did (as aforeſaid)</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That there is a God (according to the Scriptures) and that this God is the God of truth, peace and love and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it; who is called a Spirit, and whoſe throne is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.1. 1 Tim 6.16 1 King. 8.27. Jer. 23, 23, 24. Iſa. 6.3.</note> and that dwelleth in light, and which the heaven of heavens cannot contain; and who is not limitted to any time, place, or perſon; but heaven and earth is full of his glory. And ſo much for God what, and where he is.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That there is a Devil (according to the Scripture) and this Devil is the god of ſin, as of this world, which darkens all appearances of good things;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4. Rev. 20.1, 2, 3.</note> whoſe habitation is in hell and who is limitted to time, place, and perſon, and cannot go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his bounds, and is the Prince of darkneſs, and of death, the power of the ayr,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20. John 8.44. Rev. 21.8. and 12.10. John 5.45. Iude ver. 9.</note> the ſpirit ruling in the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which makes them (ſo long) to continue the children of the Devil, who is a lyar and the father of them, and all lyes and lyars are of and in him, who ſhall together with him ſuffer in hell fire; and who is alſo the accuſer of the brethren, from whom all accuſations proceed, with all hatred, envy and malice,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:199130:32"/>and hath no part in Chriſt; and that this Devil,
<note place="margin">Iam. 3.14, 15 Iohn 14.36. 1 Pet. 5.8. Gen. 3.15. Pſal. 110.5, 6</note> as a roaring lyon, goes about from City to City, from County to County, or from <hi>Worceſter</hi> to <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſeeking whom he may devour; till the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> meets with him, breaks his head, deſtroys his power, fruſtrates his deſign, and ſo ruines his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
                  <p>And Thirdly, That there is alſo a heaven for the righteous in Chriſt, to be ſaved and made happy in life and ſalvation with Chriſt in God; and there is a hell alſo for the wicked, in which they are and ſhall be tormented with the Devil and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; but for the place, what and where it is, ſo far as the Scripture is ſilent in it, we are to be ſilent in it, and cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of it any further then the Scripture doth.</p>
                  <p>But this we may ſay with the Scripture firſt, concerning hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that <hi>the Kingdom of God is righteouſneſs, peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and, <hi>Behold the Kingdom of God is within you;</hi> yet on high with God,
<note place="margin">Rom 14.1. Luke 17.20, 21.</note> above the earth or any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</p>
                  <p>And as concerning hell, it is in Scripture compared to a grave; and we read that Chriſt deſcended into it; and <hi>David</hi> ſaith to God, <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in hell</hi> (meaning the grave) <hi>nor ſuffer thy holy one to ſee corruption:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.10.</note> and what this hell and grave is, he alſo calls it the loweſt pit, or darkneſs in the deep, in which he was ſhut up, and could not come forth, the wrath of God lying ſo hard upon him,
<note place="margin">Pſalm 88.</note> or the Lord hiding his face from him; and <hi>Jonah</hi> agrees with the ſame, who when he was in the fiſhes belly, ſaid, That he was in hell; <hi>For out of the belly of hell</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>cryed I unto thee, and thou heardſt my voyce;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ionah 2.</note> 
                     <hi>for when thou hadſt caſt me into the deep</hi> (or depth of darkneſs) <hi>into the midſt of the ſea</hi> (or under many troubles and afflictions) <hi>and the floods compaſſed me about, all thy billows and thy waves paſſed over me; then I ſaid, I am caſt out of thy ſight</hi> (or ſaw thee in wrath) <hi>yet I will look again toward thy holy Temple, where I ſhall behold thee in love, when thou ſhalt raiſe me up.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos 9.2.</note> And in <hi>Amos</hi> the Lord ſaith, <hi>Though they dig into hell, thence ſhall my hand take them, and your covenant with death and hell ſhall be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulled, ſaith the Lord:</hi> But it is moſt ſure that there is a hell for the wicked, as there is a heaven for the godly, and all that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:199130:33"/>are in Chriſt Jeſus. And for this, let us conſider of one Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture more, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. where heaven is ſaid to be at the right hand of God, and hell at the left hand, compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. <hi>In thy preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at thy right hand are pleaſures for evermore</hi> (meaning in heaven with God) and how thoſe on the right hand, and that have increaſed their talents, enter into the joy of the Lord, as into heaven, where they are at reſt for ever; when thoſe on the left hand, and that have not increaſed their talents, go into utter darkneſs, as into hell, <hi>where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> pining and mourning for ſin, and where they are at no reſt.</p>
                  <p>And thus there is a heaven, wherein eternal life is enjoyed by Chriſt and all his: and there is a hell, wherein everlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is inflicted upon the Devil, and all his: But let us uſe the Scripture expreſſion for it, if we ſhall declare it, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mind of God.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>That everlaſting life ſhould end in this life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord, for anſwer to this, I do affirm, That I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (then, and ſo) ſaid the words; and I do alſo affirm, That everlaſting life with Chriſt in God, ſhall never have an end; and that believers, or the righteous in Chriſt go to it, as to God, enjoy it as God, and ſtill remain in it, as in God, with Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.4. John 3.36.</note> yea, after they have been dead, according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; as the wicked go to hell and damnation, and as ſome who believe not, are already in it: And thus life everlaſting with Chriſt in God ſhall never have an end.</p>
                  <p>Object. But for a further clearing of this, ſome may yet ſay, <hi>Is there not a life which ſhall have an end, and yet ſaid to be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, That there is a life according to manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſpoken of in Scripture, which ſeems to have an end, or be made perfect in another life, and yet ſaid to be everlaſting; as the life of works and of nature ends, and is made perfect in the life of grace; the life of grace ends, and is made perfect in the life of glory; the leſſer ſtill ſwallowed up of the greater, the lower of the higher, the darker of the lighter, the weaker of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:199130:33"/>the ſtronger, to be made perfect; and ſo at laſt all things end and are made perfect in God.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>But how is that which ends ſaid to be everlaſting?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> For further anſwer to this it may alſo be ſaid, That if the firſt Covenant and Prieſthood under the Law, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions thereof,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17. Exo. 40.13; 14, 15,</note> was ſaid to be everlaſting (as that it was and is during the time of that adminiſtration unto us) then the life which we lived in obedience to that Covenant, while under it (which was a life of works, of fear, and of bondage) was as everlaſting as that; but when that firſt Covenant and Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, with the conditions thereof, according to that admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, which was ſaid to be everlaſting (or was made perfect in a ſecond, a new, and more heavenly) then the life which we lived while under the firſt, did end alſo with the firſt, and ſo with the ſame made perfect in a ſecond, a new, and more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly life, as in life of grace and freedom, faith and love, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſecond Covenant, changed and brought in, confirmed and ſealed by the blood of the Lord Jeſus, whoſe life we then live, and are juſtified by: for where there is a change of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Law, Statute, Ordinances, Conditions, Adminiſtrations or Diſpenſations, there is a change of a life alſo to the creature, even that life which we are then bound by that Law in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to live; which is a change from a Covenant of works, to a Covenant of free grace,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.28, 29.</note> or from the circumciſing of the foreskin of the fleſh in the letter, to that of the heart, and in the ſpirit; which Covenant it is that God hath made with us (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture) and which we are to live;
<note place="margin">Heb. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>For after theſe daies</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a new Covenant will I make, &amp;c.</hi> therefore a new life will he give.</p>
                  <p>And that the word <hi>(Everlaſting)</hi> and <hi>(For ever)</hi> hath an end with us, I ſhall yet prove from ſeveral Scriptures; for in ſome Scriptures it is ſaid, <hi>The earth ſhall endure for ever;</hi> as <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. in others it is ſaid, <hi>The earth ſhall be diſſolved and burnt up:</hi> now that earth which ſhall have no end, muſt be that which had no beginning; for whatſoever hath a beginning, hath alſo an end; and what that earth is which hath neither beginning nor end, the Preacher in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> will tell you.</p>
                  <p>But there is a earth which ſhall have an end, and that is the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:199130:34"/>earth which the Devil feeds upon,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.14.</note> and inhabits in, to wit, fleſh, ſin and corruption, the old man in us, that is of the earth earthy, together with all carnal wiſdom,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.47.</note> ſelf-righteouſneſs, fleſh, form, and formality, as that which is not ſpirit and truth, and that cannot endure the fire (even God when he appeareth in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs) why this ſhall be burnt up,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> conſumed and ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the Lord as duſt before the wind; though it is ſaid to be for ever, and everlaſting; as in <hi>Habackkuk</hi> 3.6. Yet when the Lord ſhall ſo come in his glorious brightneſs, as is there ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, then ſhall all things of man, and that is earthy, be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, bow and melt before him (as is written) <hi>Before him went the peſtilence, and burning coals went forth at his feet; he ſtood and meaſured the earth, he beheld and drove aſunder the Nations, and the everlaſting mountains were ſcattered, the perpetual hills did bow;</hi> that is, the mountains of fear, ſin, death, the Devil, and mens pretended holineſs, heaven and happineſs, which is filthineſs when out of its place;
<note place="margin">Pſalm 64.6.</note> this ſhall all be ſcattered and melt before the Lord, as mountains ſtanding between the Lord and us, and as ſo many falſe gods in the way of the true God, which hath been ſaid to laſt for ever; yet theſe ſhall paſs away, and be removed out of their places into no place, but fly away from the face of him that ſits upon the throne, whoſe name is called <hi>Faithful and true,</hi> and that reigns himſelf for ever and ever, world without end.</p>
                  <p>And thus one life ends in another life, the life of the old man in the life of the new man; or we changed from life to life, from glory to glory, from one everlaſting to another, til we can change no more;
<note place="margin">Rev, 20.11.</note> which ſhews that there are more changes then one, and more everlaſtings then one (as to men) and ſo more lives then one, which men are ſaid to live, and be changed from, till they are changed from all things into God, which is their laſt change.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:199130:34"/>
                  <head>A word of Concluſion to the Iudge.</head>
                  <p>AND now laſtly, I cannot but add a few words more, and therein affirm both before God and men, that ever ſince I knew any thing of God, my whole deſign both in writing, ſpeaking and walking according to the utmoſt of my power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of God, hath ever been, and I hope ever ſhall be, ſtill to ſet forth the glory of God, the advancement of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, peace and righteouſneſs among men, and the throwing down of Antichriſt, the Devil and his Kingdom, with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs, and unrighteouſneſs of men and whatſoever elſe is and hath been contrary to the publike peace of this Nation, under which we ſhould be protected, and no longer do I deſire or ſhall endeavour to write or ſpeak a word, then that it ſhould not tend to this, even the advancement of the Kingdom of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, without partiality, or aiming at any private or ſelf-intereſt of my own or an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> others diſtinct, but for the publike good of all men, whom I deſire and do ſtill endeavour in love to ſerve being made willing to ſpend and be ſpent for them, notwithſtanding the many reproaches, revilings and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions I meet withal; yet ſtill that I would continue a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant to the truth in all things, by which I am made free to ſerve in love and for which I am not only ready to be bound, but to ſuffer.</p>
                  <p>All which particulars according to your Lordſhips deſire, I do moſt humbly preſent you with before this honourable Court, and ſo leave them to your conſideration, to do as the Lord of heaven and earth ſhall direct you who works all things according to the counſel of his own will, and will glorifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in all things that himſelf doth.</p>
                  <p>And now what ſhall I ſay more? why let the Lords will be done, whether in life or death, in freedom or impriſonment, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own will and pleaſure be it, into whoſe bleſſed arms of mercy, love, joy, and peace. I do freely give up my ſelf, and ſhall for ever lodge in his boſom of life and ſalvation, there to reſt and abide for ever.</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:199130:35"/>
                  <p>While I was making my anſwer, my accuſers with many others of their conſorts, did all the time of my pleading interrupt me, urging many things to me to inſnare me, and to incenſe the Judge and Jury againſt me, till the Judge reproved them for it, who after he had heard my anſwer, and underſtanding it, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it alſo not to come within the compaſs of any late Act of Parliament, and withal perceiving the malice of my enemies, did as the Lord had directed him, who before the petty Jury went forth to conſult upon their verdict (who underſtood it not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, neither what they had to do in ſuch a buſineſs, being all ignorant men both of the Law, and of ſuch things) acquainted them with the truth of the buſineſs, that ſo Juſtice and Equity might take place, whoſe directions were according to what follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Judge.</hi> You of the Jury, you have heard the evidence, and you have heard the anſwer of his defence, which if what he hath ſaid to us be his meaning, it is very good, and what I believe my ſelf to be truth, and we are to take his ſenſe and meaning upon the words, and not anothers, the words being his own: but ſhould we take the very expreſs words of the Indictment, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a qualification of them, yet it comes not under the Law, or Act of Parliament, according to the rule of which Act we are to go; as for the firſt thing, that he ſhould ſay Chriſt dyed for his own ſins, it comes not neer it, though indeed the ſecond concerning heaven and hell comes ſomething neer it, yet not ſo neer as to be found within the compaſs of it; for the Act ſaith, if a man avow and affirm that there is no heaven and hell; but that he doth not, and this alſo was by way of diſpute or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence after Sermon, as you ſee the witneſſes to the Bill do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs; and what is ſaid in diſpute, cannot be ſaid to be avowed and affirmed, for it may fall in by way of an Argument, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as to the laſt words, that everlaſting life ſhould end in this life, there is nothing mentioned in the Act againſt it; therefore we are not to meddle with it, and you are not to bring him in guilty for any thing he is here indicted, it being not within the compaſs of the Act.</p>
                  <p>And thus with other words to that purpoſe, did the Judge
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:199130:35"/>ſpeak to the Jury before they gave in their verdict, which none that heard it but thought it had been ſufficient to have ſatisfied any honeſt Jury in the world, had they been but rational men; yet it ſatisfied not theſe, for they malitiouſly brought me in guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who were prompt to it by my accuſers and others that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them forth of the Court, contradicting the words of the Judge, ſaying that they were not to take notice of what the Judge had ſaid, neither of my anſwer, but the Bill. Being asked the reaſon why they brought me in guilty; they ſaid they could do no leſs, they were ſo followed by the Prieſts from place to place and importuned to it, that they could be at no quiet for them unleſs they did it. A wiſe Jury, to be ſworn and then ſwayed by other men! but this they did to do the Prieſts a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt me, as <hi>Feſtus</hi> did to do the Jews a pleaſure againſt <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 25.9.</p>
                  <p>Then the Judge examined them what crime they found me guilty of: they anſwered they could not tell what but according to the evidence; then ſaid the Iudge, doth the thing evidenced come within the compaſs of the Act? who again cauſed the Act to be read to them and bid them take notice of it; yet they could not tell what crime I was guilty of, but ſtill ſaid according to the Evidence; then the Iudge asked them what the Evidence was, and they could not declare it tell they were told it: and now how unfit theſe men are to be made a Iury of ſuch things, let all men that hear it take notice.</p>
                  <p>Then the Iudge as before (perceiving their ignorance) ſhewed them how it came not within the compaſs of the Act, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not to be found; then ſaid the Iury, we will referr it to you: Nay ſaid the Iudge, I muſt have your verdict: Not guilty then, ſaid ſome of the Iury; others ſaid guilty; what are you divided (ſaid the Iudge) I will not receive your verdict till you are agreed, and unleſs you will agree upon it, you ſhall be ſhut up together in one room all night, where you ſhall have neither bread nor beer, fire nor candle.</p>
                  <p>But when they heard this, they began to murmur within themſelves why they ſhould not agree, yet the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge willing to ſhew them favour, did only rebuke them, bidding them to bring in their verdict the next morning by eight of the clock, upon pain
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:199130:36"/>of twenty pound a piece, and where I was then alſo my ſelf to appear, and there according to the requeſt of the Judge I was to give in the heads of my anſwer in writing, which then did, and it was there read to the ſatisfaction of the Court.</p>
                  <p>Then the Jury being again called, before they gave in their Verdict, uſed the name or one <hi>Veyſie</hi> of <hi>Tainton</hi> neer <hi>Burford,</hi> which (ſaid they) deſires to be a witneſs againſt him, for ſaying that Chriſt was the cauſe of <hi>Cains</hi> fall.</p>
                  <p>No ſaid the Judge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> will hear no ſuch malitious fellows, but will keep cloſe to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndictment; and you of the Jury are to mention none, but to give in your Verdict: then ſaid they, guilty.</p>
                  <p>Now the Judge well knowing the Law, and how that thoſe things came not within the compaſs of it; alſo perceiving the malice of my accuſers and the ignorance of the Jury in ſuch things, as was then manifeſted; and himſelf willing to do juſtice, took bayl for my appearance at the next Aſſizes, at which my accuſers began to fall mad, crying out again for my impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, baniſhment or ſilencing, but the Judge told them he could do neither, but muſt go according to the Law, and the Law did not require any ſuch thing.</p>
                  <p>Then my accuſers to lay another foundation again to enſnare me, having miſſed the former, preſented to the Judge a paper, wherein were many particular points of their own judgement, that he ſhould prevail upon me to ſet my hand to it, as that which I would own for truth, thereby to confirm theirs, &amp; I never more to preach againſt the ſame; but this being offered to me, I refuſed it, and deſired not to ſet my hand to other mens writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but to what I write my ſelf, unleſs I may read it, and alſo find it to be truth according to the Scripture and my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; then ſaid the Judge (in the preſence of my accuſers) take it and read it; which I did and gave it to the Iudge again; and becauſe my accuſers with others, reported that I ſet my hand to all that they had writ, as a recantation of what my ſelf formerly writ, and declared: therefore for the ſatisfaction of other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the proving of them lyers, and clearing my ſelf in it, it is here publiſhed both what they writ, and alſo what part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I refuſed, and what I ſigned diſtinctly as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paper">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:199130:36"/>
                  <head>A Paper written by my Accuſers and preſented to the Judge for me to ſign, which I would not.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHereas at ſeveral paſſages in a printed book that goes forth in my name, and in a publike diſcovery at</hi> Enſton <hi>about</hi> Iune <hi>laſt, ſeveral perſons have been offended, and been induced to believe that I am guilty of holding and publiſhing blaſphemous opinions; for the ſatisfying all ſuch perſons, and clearing my ſelf, I do heartily and ſincerely profeſs and declare againſt them, as follows.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt, That Jeſus Chriſt the only begotten Son of God, being eternal God and equal with the Father, did in the fulneſs of time take to himſelf mans nature; yet without ſin; being holy, harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, undefiled, as the Scripture ſaith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly, The Lord Ieſus Chriſt for diſcharging the office of Mediatorſhip whereunto he was called by his Father, did perfectly fulfill the Law, indured the ſhameful and curſed death of the croſs, but not for himſelf, being perfectly free from ſin, but that he might ſatisfie for the ſins of his people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly, The third day he roſe from the dead with the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with which he ſuffered; with which alſo he aſcended into heaven, and there ſitteth at the right hand of his Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly, The bodies of men after death return to duſt, but their ſouls which die not, return to God who gave them; the ſouls of the righteous are received into the higheſt heaven where they enjoy God in glory, waiting for the full redemption of their bodies; and the ſouls of the wicked are caſt into hell, where they remain in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſerved to the Iudgement of the great day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly, At the laſt day ſuch as are found alive, ſhall be changed; and all that are dead ſhall be raiſed up with the ſame body, which ſhall be united again to their ſouls for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly, God hath appointed a day wherein he will judge the world in righteouſneſs by Jeſus Chriſt, in which day the Apoſtles and Angels ſhall be judged, and all perſons that have lived upon the earth ſhall appear before the Tribunal of Chriſt, to give an account of their thoughts, words and deeds, and to receive according to what they have done in their bodies, whether good or evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:199130:37"/>
                  <p>Theſe things I believe, and do not publiſh any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to them; and for any paſſages that have fell from me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theſe ignorantly, inconſiderately, or wilfully I do profeſs my ſelf troubled at and aſhamed of but this I excepted againſt, and would not ſet my hand unto as follows.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, there are ſome things which I may ſet my hand unto, but there are ſome things that are falſe and I ſhall not ſet my hand to that, unleſs they will here make it good by Scripture before this honourable Court.</p>
                  <p>Then ſaid the Judge to me; What is that you ſay is falſe which you except againſt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irſt wherein they ſay ſeveral paſſages have been written and ſpoken by me, to the inducement of ſeveral perſons to believe that I am guilty of holding and publiſhing blaſphemous opinions, which they would now have me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt, and profeſs my ſelf aſhamed of: when I know nothing that ever I ſpoke or writ ſince the time of my call, that I went forth to declare any thing of God that was ſo or ever could be proved blaſphemy by them, though they have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to do it, therefore not to be declared againſt by me.</p>
                  <p>My Lord; Another thing in the fifth particular which they declare as their judgement is, that the ſame body which dyes, ſhall after death be ſo raiſed again and united to the ſoul for ever; which thing is falſe my Lord, and I know no Scripture to prove it; if there be, let them produce it, for here they are.</p>
                  <p>Then the Judge (looking upon them) asked if there were no ſuch Scripture; but they were ſilent and anſwered not a word; then Juſtice <hi>Jenkins</hi> who ſate upon the bench, undertook to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for them, and ſaid, there is ſuch a Scripture: produce it you then, ſaid I, and let me ſee it, or I ſhall not believe it; but he was ſilent alſo, and there was no man to be found that could ſhew that Scripture; then I inſtanced a Scripture in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. to the contrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that the ſame body was not to riſe again, but God giveth it a body as pleaſeth him, which body none of them yet knew.</p>
                  <p>Then the Judge perceiving that thoſe things which by them were written, and by me excepted againſt, could not by them
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:199130:37"/>nor any other be proved, he commanded them to be croſſed forth before their faces, and they had nothing to ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves which was to the great ſhame and diſgrace of my accuſers, and others of their tribe, that thoſe things which they have ſo long held forth and maintained to the people for truth, and as their judgments, that this ſhould now be croſſed out before their faces as an error; ſure as bad a thing as ever they could have done againſt themſelves in things of that nature; which makes it to appear, that the greateſt blaſphemer cryed blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my firſt, and theſe things being croſſed out, I ſet my hand to the reſt, which is as follows, and which to my knowledge I never declared any thing contrar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to, according to the Scriptures, and in a ſpiritual ſenſe, in which ſenſe we are to underſtand all things of that nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="doctrinal_statement">
                  <head>The part culars which I ſigned.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FIrſt, that Ieſus Chriſt the only begotten ſon of God, being eternal God and equal with the Father, did in the fulneſs of time take to himſelf mans nature yet without ſin, being holy, harmleſs, undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as the ſcripture ſaith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly, The Lord ſeſus Chriſt for diſcharging the office of Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atorſhip, whereunto he was called by his Father, did perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfill the Law, endured the ſhameful and curſed death of the croſs, but not for himſelf, being (as he was) perfectly free from ſin; but that he might ſatisfie for the ſin of his people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly, The third day he roſe from the dead with the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with which he ſuffered, with which alſo he aſcended into heaven,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>and there ſitteth at the right hand of his Father (but not with fleſh and blood.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly, The bodies of men after death return to duſt, but their ſouls which die not return to God who gave them; the ſouls of the righteous are received into the higheſt heaven, where they enjoy God in glory, waiting for the full redemption of their bodies; and the ſouls of the wicked are caſt into hell, where they remain in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment reſerved to the Judgment of the great day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly, At the laſt day, ſuch as are found alive ſhall be
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:199130:38"/>changed, and they that are dead ſhall be raiſed up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly, God hath appointed a day wherein he will Judge the world in righteouſneſs by Jeſus Chriſt, which day the Apoſtate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhall be Iudged, and all perſons that live upon the earth, ſhall appear before the tribunal of Chriſt, to give an account of their thoughts, words and deeds, and to receive according to what they have done in their bodies, whether good or evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe things I do believe (according to the Scriptures) and never publiſh any thing contrary to them.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Richard Coppin.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>The Authors ſecond appearing at</hi> Oxford <hi>Aſſiſes before Judge</hi> Hutton, <hi>and what was there done.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I According to my engagement appeared the ſecond time at the general Aſſiſes holden at <hi>Oxford,</hi> there expecting again to have ſeen the faces of my former accuſers, they having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid they would follow me to death; but they finding nothing againſt me came not there; &amp; proclamation being made in the Court for my diſcharge, and none other having any thing againſt me to declare, one <hi>Keat</hi> the then Sheriff for that County, ſitting in the Court, being of a bitter ſpirit, and alſo an enemy to truth, as he then appeared, ſtood up as one among the reſt of the accuſers and informers, ſaying that he could declare ſomething againſt me, which was ſpoke in <hi>London;</hi> but when he was asked what it was, no particular could be mention, but ſaid that he had heard very ſtrange things declared by me at S. <hi>Dunſtons</hi> Church in <hi>London,</hi> before a great Congregation of people of great qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to the great diſhonour of God, and the people diſturbance, as ſaid this informer Mr. <hi>Keet,</hi> who earneſtly importuned the Judge to reſtrain me from preaching; in anſwer to which the Judge told him that a mans liberty was pretious, and there was no reaſon any man ſhould be reſtrained from his liberty therein,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:199130:38"/>by any mans words whatſoever, unleſs oath were made againſt him that he had offended the Law. Therefore (ſaid the Judge) I cannot do it upon your words, nor any mans elſe; for then I ſhould be partial, and I came not onely to bind, but to free men</p>
               <p>Then the Informer Mr. <hi>Keat</hi> by name receiving thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes from the Judge, was ſilent, and ſate him down with ſhame, and then the bitter ſpirits of others in the Univerſity, whoſe mouthes were ready to be opened in malice againſt me, were quaſhed, my freedom ordered, and my enemies aſhamed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors humble appeal to his Highneſs</hi> Oliver <hi>Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>as a General redreſs for all people.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>FOraſmuch as it hath pleaſed the Lord of Lords to call you to this high place of Protectorſhip (under himſelf) and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he ſhall protect, counſel, guide and direct you, as he did Chriſt and the reſt of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo you may act like them in walking before the people to do juſtice among them; <hi>For by him Kings reign, and Princes decree juſtice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> 
                  <hi>who himſelf reigns in them to be their wonderful Counſellor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, as according to the counſel of the Lord, your Highneſs hath been pleaſed to declare your ſelf both by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and oath to ſeek the peace, freedom and liberty of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this and other Nations againſt oppreſſion and tyranny, and to protect them in their juſt rights and priviledges, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the mind of God written in Scripture for Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that then (in the Lords time) and as he himſelf ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to go before you, and act in you, ſo you may according to his directions follow him in perſuit thereof, bringing glory to God in the higheſt, and on earth peace, and good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:199130:39"/>
               <p>Which you ſhall, ſo far as you follow the counſel of the Lord, and not of men,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.1.</note> who are to be counſelled by you, and not you by them; and men in their counſel towards you, are onely to aſſiſt you in carrying on that work which the Lord ſhall adviſe and counſel you in; whoſe counſel ſhall ſtand, and he will do all his pleaſure, when men and their counſel ſhall fail: for as he himſelf hath choſen you, and ſhall put his ſpirit within you to inſtruct and counſel you; ſo will he himſelf be with you to protect you, that you in him may protect his people, and therein become a nurſing father (in him) to them, to increaſe among them their juſt freedom and liberty in the Lord Jeſus.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 49, 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>That this freedom of theirs, as it is in the Lord, and wrought by the Lord is not to be ſetled or eſtabliſhed upon any one ſort of people, under any one form of Religion whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, any further then the Lord hath called them, and ſhall himſelf eſtabliſh it in them, but all are to have like freedom, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeveral Diſpenſations or Adminiſtrations they yet appear to live under,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.12, 13, 14.</note> according to the meaſure of the gift of God, in their ſeveral places, or degrees of callings; as they are either children, young men, or fathers in the faith of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And you, like Chriſt to be a nurſing Father to them all, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having reſpect to particular times, places, perſons and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, or any degree of calling whatſoever diſtinct, but to aſſiſt and protect all whoſe practice is not licentious, and who in their ways are not deſtructive to true love, peace and unity among men.</p>
               <p>And how you are not to hinder any, but to further all that doth any thing of the work of the Lord, for the glory of God, and the good of one another; and ſo according to the example of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 42.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> you are not to break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking flax, to deſtroy thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſave them, &amp; as much as in you lies follow peace with all men, ſeek to increaſe &amp; blow up the coals of divine love among them, that ſo both you and they may alike walk together in the light of God, and live in the power of divine life, and ſo be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered up with the arms, and carried in the boſom of him that gently leads thoſe that are with yong,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.11.</note> and by the ſame power
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:199130:39"/>may be enabled to do the ſame work of love one for another,
<note place="margin">Mal. 2 10. Acts 17 28 Epheſ. 4.6.</note> to live and act in the ſame life, that ſhall bring joy and comfort to each other, having all one God, and one Father, in whom we all live, move, and have our being: and who is over all, through all, and in all, God bleſſed for ever.</p>
               <p>And now that your Highneſs cannot be ignorant of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and cruelty that the free-born people of the Lord yet lie under, and is ſtill continued againſt them by a generation of oppreſſive people that would ſtill Lord it over their lives, liberties and eſtates; and endeavour to bring all men to their own ways and cuſtoms, and ſo keep their poor brethren in bondage and ſlavery ſtill under them, never ſuffering the freedom of Chriſt to break forth, in and among his people; but inſtead of increaſing the light and liberty thereof, they rather ſeek to quench and inthral it.</p>
               <p>But this I know, and therefore am at peace in my ſelf, that the Lord Jeſus will ſuddenly ariſe with deliverance for his people, to bring them out of their captivity, into their glorious liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo reſtore peace to all men, and himſelf then reign as a Prince of peace in all Nations.</p>
               <p>This work of the Lord, for the glory of God, and good of all people, which is now to be done, you know to be recorded in the 58. Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> from the 6. verſe to the end; and the reward that will follow the accompliſhment of this work: which work, ſaith the Prophet, is, <hi>to looſe the bands of wickedneſs, to undo the heavy burthens, and to let the oppreſſed go free, &amp;c. and that ye break every yoke; alſo to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are caſt out to thy houſe; when thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thy own fleſh, &amp;c. then ſhall thy light break fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th as the morning, and thine health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedily, and thy righteouſneſs ſhall go before thee, and the glory of the Lord ſhall be thy reward, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That then according (as this is to be done,) as God ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able you, and in every thing fit and qualifie you for this work of his, ſo you may as a juſt and impartial Governor in the hands of the Lord, be pleaſed to come forth in a general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs for all people to make good this good work of the Lord,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:199130:40"/>which he hath been pleaſed to put you upon the promiſe of for the deliverance of his people, that ſo under your protection they may live ſecurely, walk chearfully, and ſit down contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that which makes moſt for the peace of their own ſouls, the ſafety of their bodies, and the happy ſucceſs one of another in the Lord Jeſus, to the end that God both from your ſelf, and all others, may in all things have all the glory; his people, peace and freedom one with another, and you the reward of a true ſervant of the Lord</p>
               <p>And therefore now inaſmuch as by your Highneſs (in whoſe hands under God the power of this and other Nations is at this time ſeated, the Lord hath been pleaſed to promiſe a perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this work, give me leave to proceed in this humble ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to your Highneſs, to ſet before you ſome abuſes offered againſt the Laws and Liberties of the people now under your protection, as will appear in that which follows; and how ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my experience the people of God have always ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the teſtimony of Jeſus, in preſsing after, and walking in their liberty in him, which thoſe that knew it not, ever did, and ſtill do oppoſe.</p>
               <p>And that upon conſideration thereof, you may to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of your endeavour in the Lord Jeſus, ſtand by his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to relieve them, protect, ſupport and defend them in their juſt rights and priviledges, their lives, liberties and eſtates, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their enemies that oppoſe them, you will evermore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the hearts of the free born people of the Lord, in love to ſerve you, as you in love and the preſence of God ſhall ſerve them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the God of love and peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> give patience to all his people to wait upon the Lord, for what he in his own time ſhal be pleaſed to bring forth by you:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.16.</note> and then <hi>he that believes, ſhall not need to make haſte.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:199130:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſufferings of Chriſt, his Prophets, and Apoſtles, together with the Authors ſufferings, briefly diſcovered and preſented to his Highneſs, in his humble Appeal.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ACcording to the Declaration of Scripture, we find, that whatſoever of truth hath at any time been held forth or declared by any to whom God hath made himſelf known, that the publiſhers thereof were ſufferers therein: This we find in the truth it ſelf, the Lord Jeſus; for declaring himſelf in love to men, was always a ſufferer by men, who underſtood him not;
<note place="margin">Mat 2.</note> for from the firſt day of his birth, that he was but reported to be the Son of God, did <hi>Herod,</hi> together with the chief Prieſts and Phariſes, ſend forth after him to deſtroy him; and the more of God or that divine life there appeared in him, the more did they ſeek to take his life away from him; not for the envy they had to his perſon onely, but to that life which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the life of God manifeſted in him, which life they knew not; <hi>For had they known him, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory:</hi> but they knew him not, neither would they own his life, and power to be of God, but rather of the Devil; for ſaid they, <hi>He caſteth out Devils through the Prince of Devils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 9 34.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Chriſt himſelf tells us, that <hi>ſo they did by his Prophets that were before him, ſome they ſtoned, and put to death;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.11.12</note> 
                  <hi>others they perſecuted;</hi> even ſo is it now.</p>
               <p>The like appeared in his Apoſtles, who after their converſion, that they were called to the preaching of the Goſpel, what ſufferings, ſtripes, bonds and impriſonments, did they undergo for their faithfulneſs therein? and thus hath it been ever ſince to this day, with thoſe that have been faithful,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.9, 10 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16</note> in holding forth any thing of the love of God manifeſt in them, by Jeſus Chriſt, for the glory of God, and peace of all men.</p>
               <p>And now ſince the day that the Lord Jeſus had made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:199130:41"/>known to me, and I by the power of his living in me, as the leaſt and worſt of all Saints, have been made to go forth, proclaim, publiſh and declare freel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the world and ſinners, the unchangeable love of the Lord Jeſus, according to that meaſure of the gift given me by him: I have uffered with Chriſt, in exerciſing the gifts of Chriſt, which according to the manifeſtation of that life and power in me, I have publiſhed and declared, not for price nor reward of men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but freely, and in love to the Lord Jeſus and his people, as can be witneſſed by the people of thoſe parts into which I have come: And to ſatisfie any that ſhall queſtion the truth of what I hold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God, and the things of God, and that have not at all heard me ſpeak thereof, and now have any deſire to know my principle,
<note place="margin">Of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral Books written by me.</note> judgement or doctrine therein. I ſhall direct them to ſeveral Books of my writing now extant; the one is called <hi>Devine Teachings,</hi> in which there are three together; the other, <hi>Mans Righteouſneſs examined, and wherein found too light, reproved;</hi> a third, <hi>Saul ſmitten, for not ſmiting Amaleck, &amp;c.</hi> a fourth, <hi>A Man Childe born, or God man feſt in fleſh:</hi> And what is therein written, is the ſame that I ſtill am in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for which I have hitherto ſuffered, been indicted, falſly accuſed, ſlandered reproached and reviled, and for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Aſſizes kept bound, by a party of the Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and enemies of Chriſt, who live by the gain they make of the people; and who have appeared to be the chief inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and agents for the promoting of wars and diviſions amongſt men, to advance their own intereſts; with whom I have alſo had ſeveral diſputes, contentions and controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies about Religion, I being ingaged by them, who ſought thereby the overthrow both of me and the things of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in me; but they not prevailing againſt me, have much abuſed me, and ſeveral times charged me with blaſphemy, brought me before Rulers, Counſels, and Judges of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes, twice at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and twice at <hi>Oxford:</hi> where they laid their ſeveral accuſations of blaſphemy (as they ſaid) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; but could never be proved by any Law to be ſo: whereupon, according to the will of God, I was ſtill deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, both by Law and Judges, the Lord enabling me to ſpeak
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:199130:41"/>for my ſelf; and alſo working upon the hearts and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Judges, to underſtand the anſwer by me made, and thereby free me from the cruelty of my enemies, though ſtill found guilty by the Juries, who themſelves underſtood it not (being alſo prompt by my adverſaries, as ſeveral witneſſes can teſtifie) and for which the ſaid Juries were reproved by the Judges in the open Court: The particulars of which tryals I ſhall preſent to the world more at large hereafter.</p>
               <p>Thus for my faithfulneſs to the truth, have I ſuffered by my enemies, who behind the backs of the Judges did accuſe them for injuſtice, concerning my deliverance, when according to law and juſtice they did act and that theſe my enemies have ſince vowed (by me,
<note place="margin">Acts 23.12.</note> as the Jews did by <hi>Paul</hi>) they would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to death, as can alſo be proved by ſeveral witneſſes; for the performance of which vow, and to a further diſcovery of their malice towards me, and the truth revealed in me, they yet ceaſe not to follow me, with endeavours to make good this their evil intentions againſt me; but rather then they will want ſomething whereby to accuſe me (for which they have watched daily over me,
<note place="margin">Luke 6.7.</note> as the Scribes and Phariſees did over Chriſt) Judge <hi>Green</hi> (one of the former Judges, being dead) they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported they would again revive ſome of the former accuſations againſt me, and ſo again bring me to a tryal thereof: Their il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal and unjuſt proceedings will appear in that which follows, in the reading of which, I ſhall humbly crave and deſire your patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:199130:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A further diſcovery to his Highneſs, of the malitious practiſes, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant cenſurs, and illegal proceedings of two Juſtices and certain miniſters at</hi> Stow <hi>on the</hi> Old <hi>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> loceſterſhiere, <hi>March</hi> 19. 1653. <hi>againſt the ſuffering Author.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>VPon the ninteenth day of <hi>March</hi> laſt paſt, being the Lords day, I (through the deſire and earneſt requeſt of very many of the Town and Pariſh of <hi>Stow</hi> on the <hi>Old</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and by ſeveral other of the neighbour Pariſhes and Towns neer adjacent) was at <hi>Stow,</hi> where I was to preach, to anſwer the deſires of thoſe people that were there, and that deſired me to come, where and at which time I went to the Church or common me ting place in the morning and heard one Mr. <hi>Elmes</hi> then Miniſter of <hi>Winchcombe</hi> preach who there delivering ſomething contrary to truth, and having ended his Sermon that the people were departing, I with his conſent, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him a queſtion as follows.</p>
               <p>Sir, Inaſmuch as by the providence of God and the civil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of many people, I am here this day, and at this time a hearer of you, I ſhall, if I may in love be admitted in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, be a ſpeaker, if not in this place, then in ſome other place where the Lord ſhall direct us; for to that end and purpoſe was I invited to Town this day.</p>
               <p>He anſwered, that he himſelf was a ſtranger and could not grant it, but ſaid that he thought I had had ſomething to ſay againſt his Doctrine: to which I anſwered, I had; and ſo ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him his error, I declared againſt it, that the people might not be deceived by it.</p>
               <p>For that which he ſaid was this, as the whole Congregation can witneſs that God feeding his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> as a Lamb in a large place, was his leaving of them to themſelves, a letting them looſe to all manner of ſin and wickedneſs to run head long
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:199130:42"/>into hell; which appearing to me ſo groſs an error, I could not let it paſs; but anſwered, that God feeding his people Iſrael as a Lamb in a large place, was an enlargement of the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his love and favour to them in Chriſt Jeſus, in their return to him from their backſliding condition; it was a bringing of them into that City and Sion of the living God,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 33.21.</note> where the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Lord himſelf will be unto us a place of broad Rivers and ſtreams, and then ſhall we run the way of his Commandments, (and not our own) when he hath enlarged our hearts; and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fed by God as Lambs, cannot be ſaid to be left of God or forſaken, but are fed with Chriſt who is their daily bread from heaven, and God cannot be ſaid to feed his people,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.32. Iſa. 24 14.</note> when he is ſaid to leave them; but according to your own principle you will ſay, that thoſe that are let looſe unto all manner of ſin and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes, to run headlong into h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, are not fed by God but the Devil.</p>
               <p>And now anſwer being thus made in as civil a manner as could be, and there being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſent one <hi>John Crofty</hi> and <hi>Richard Aylworth,</hi> Juſtices of the Peace for that County, who hearing this my ſpeech made to their Miniſter, were much moved and enraged in their ſpirits againſt me, as appeared by their rude and uncivil carriage at that time towards me who alſo ſaid I ſhould have ſpoke to their Miniſter in private and not in publike; to which I anſwered that no time and place was ſo fit as then and there, the people being preſent; for truth ſeeks no corners; whereupon the ſaid Juſtices to carry on their deſign of a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceeding againſt me, did immediately charge the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables with me, commanding them to bring me into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters houſe, where they and <hi>Elmes</hi> the ſaid Miniſter was, and ſo commanding the doors to be ſhut, they deſired I would anſwer ſome queſtions which they ſhould propound; I told them that what they had to propound in love and for edification to any, I ſhould a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r them; which was as follows.</p>
               <p>Firſt Queſtion; Whether I did believe there was a God, and a Devil-a heaven and a hell? I anſwered, that there was both God and Devil, Heaven and Hell,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.5, 6.</note> ſalvation and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and I further ſaid that there were alſo Gods many and Lords many in the world, known as to men and worſhipt by
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:199130:43"/>men,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.23.</note> though but one true God and him moſt men did ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhip.</p>
               <p>Another queſtion they asked me, whether God would ſave all men or no? I anſwered, that what the Scripture ſaid I would ſay; and the Scripture ſaid of God, that he <hi>will have all men to be ſaved,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4, 5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and to come unto the knowledge of the truth; for there is one God and one Mediator between God and men, the man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who gave himſelf a ranſom for all, to be teſtified in due time;</hi> but we ſee that all men are not yet ſaved; for all men have not yet this teſtimony, or do not yet believe, for he that believes not is condemned already,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.18. 1 Ioh 5 10. Rev. 1 5.</note> and he that doth believe hath the witneſs in himſelf and this witneſs is Chriſt.</p>
               <p>A third queſtion was; Whether I did believe there were three perſons in the Trinity? The Trinity I acknowledged; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of them what they meant by perſon, whether a material body of fleſh and bones or not? To which they did not anſwer; but asked me again, if there were not three diſtinct beings? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh 5.7, 8.</note> that according to Scripture there were three that bear witneſs in heaven, and three that bear witneſs on earth, and each three did agree in one; ſo that there was but one being of all things, and that being was eternal; then they asked me what the three that bear witneſs in heaven were, and whether they were not three perſons? I anſwered that according to Scripture they were known by the name of Father, Son and Spirit, and were three in reſpect of manifeſtation to the creature, and yet but one in union and being with the Creator and Father of all things: they again asked me how far theſe three were diſtinct one from another? I anſwered, that ſo far as the Father is from the Son,
<note place="margin">Ioh 14 10, 11.</note> and the Son from the Father, ſo far are they diſtinct one from another.</p>
               <p>And thus they provoking and urging me with many queſtions, ſought to enſare me, as it is written the Scribes and Phariſees did by Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.53, 54.</note> 
                  <hi>laying wait for him, and ſeeking to catch ſomething out of his mouth that they might accuſe him:</hi> but I anſwered as the Lord did enable me, and according to Scripture.</p>
               <p>And now I having thus anſwered to their queſtions, and they therein receiving nothing againſt me, told me that I had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſpoken things that were blaſphemy, and they would
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:199130:43"/>queſtion me for that; I told them again that nothing of blaſphemy could ever yet be proved againſt me, though endeavoured by my enemies; and what I had been formerly charged with as blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; I have already anſwered, and now ſhould at any time be ready in love to anſwer them or any other that ſhould ask me a reaſon of the hope that is in me; and the practiſe of Chriſtians (as they profeſſed themſelves to be) I told them was not to lay violent hands on any, charging Officers with them, for ſpeaking of the things of God in a way contrary to their judgement or apprehenſions; and ſo to make a man an offender for a word,
<note place="margin">Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.21.</note> and how we never found in Scripture thar A Chriſtian living in the Faith of the Lord Jeſus, did ever perſecute, accuſe, charge, judge or condemn any in point of worſhip towards God, but were themſelves alwayes accuſed, judged and condemned by others that believed not; and men may differ in opinion or judgement of things, and yet be good Chriſtians; but though we may thus differ, yet let us be reconciled together in love, and not Judge one another; for love is a fulfilling of the whole Law; and not to love is a breach of the Law.</p>
               <p>And (ſaid I) as I have heard your Miniſter, ſo both him and you if you pleaſe may in like manner hear me; and if I ſhall erre in any thing I ſpeak, then you have your liberty to ſhew me wherein, and we in love to diſcourſe it forth before the people, which thing might tend much to the glory of God and the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication one of another; but this they refuſed, and would not grant, but told me that unleſs I would come to Church in the afternoon, and hear their Miniſter without objecting any thing againſt him, they would ſtill keep me as a Priſoner; to which I anſwered, that unleſs I might ſpeak as well as hear, having an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity when their Miniſter had done, I would not come, but would in ſome other place ſpeak what God ſhould make known to me: and I further ſaid, that the Antichriſtian Law of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling men to Church, was not now in force, but men were to have their liberty therein; whereupon they gave the Conſtables further charge of me, commanding me not to ſpeak anywhere within their liberty; and they not to ſuffer any people to come neer me, nor I to come to them for that day, and in the time of their afternoon exerciſe, they commanded me to be kept cloſe priſoner, which I was for above two hours, as will further
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:199130:44"/>appear in that which follows; all which proceedings of theirs ſeems much contrary to what your Highneſs hath been pleaſed to declare in your 36. Article in the 43. page of <hi>The Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths Government,</hi> ſigned by your Highneſs <hi>Decemb.</hi> 16. 1653. that none ſhould be compelled by penalty or otherwaies to the publike profeſſion held forth and that all Laws contrary to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty were to be null and void, how contrary were theſe mens actions then to that?</p>
               <p>But the Conſtables being preſent all a long from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this buſineſs, who ſeeing and hearing all that paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, and finding no evil or miſdemeanor on my part com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, yet were alwayes in my company, were themſelves wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hear me; and the people both of Town &amp; Country being many, and no houſe there able to contain them, they before one of the clock that day were aſſembled together in the ſtreet, the number of which were ſuppoſed by many people to be neer one thouſand, to whom began my diſcourſe thus.</p>
               <p>Friends, The afternoon Sermon being not yet began at Church, and becauſe we will not be idle, I ſhall in the mean time, while we have an opportunity, ſpeak ſomething to you for your ſouls edification and comfort; and then you that will go to the Church may; and this I ſhall alſo deſire of you while you are here, that nothing may be ſaid or done on your parts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the preſent power and publike peace of this Nation, by which we ſhould be protected in this our Godly exerciſe; and you that are Officers, take notice of any that ſhall in this our meeting make any diſturbance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But after half an hours ſpace that I had proceeded thus in ſpeaking to the people, Mr. <hi>Crofts</hi> and Mr. <hi>Aylworth</hi> the ſaid Juſtices, and <hi>Elmes</hi> the ſaid Miniſter, with their horſes came ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in amongſt the people in a tumultuous manner, &amp; diſturbed the whole company, laid violent hands on me, commanding the people to aſſiſt them in it, who refuſed, but rather endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to perſwade the diſturbers of the peace (at that time) to be quiet, the people ſtill calling upon me to ſpeak on, and they would ſtill hear, in the interim two maſtive Dogs fall on the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices horſes, as if they had known them to be the diſturbers of the people. Then the ſaid Juſtices departed a little from the company; but <hi>Elmes</hi> the ſaid Miniſter urged them again not to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:199130:44"/>depart away till they had diſmiſſed our meeting; whereupon they came again in like manner as before; and while a Warrant was a preparing to apprehend me, they with ſome others would not let me go on in my former diſcourſe, but would engage me upon a diſpute, taking an occaſion to quarrel with me for preaching with my Hat on my head, though in the ſtreet, and ſaid it was contrary to the rule of the Goſpel. I demanded of them what was meant by head; they ſaid the head of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; to which I anſwered, that it was not that head meant in the Goſpel: if it were, then any thing on the head were a covering; but your Miniſter had this morning a Cap on his head, when he both preached and prayed, therefore was his head covered; and no greater diſhonour could I at this time give to my head then to keep my hat off, having no cap to put on, for the wind blows very cold; beſides the Sun ſhines full in my face; but that this is not the head there meant, conſider; for it is written that the head of every man is Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.4.</note> and Chriſt is the wiſdom and power by which all men ſhould both pray and propheſie; and any mand praying or prophecying without this, having Chriſt his head covered, vailed or hid in him, and not manifeſt in him or known by him,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.23.</note> all that he ſpeaks and asks in pretence for Chriſt, is to the diſhonour of Chriſt; and any man having thus his head covered, he diſhonours his head.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid the Juſtices in anſwer to this: O horrible blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my! what, will you ſay that Chriſt is the head of every man, and that he may be covered? you ſhall anſwer for this at <hi>Gloceſter;</hi> and ſo they preſented to the Conſtables a Warrant to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend me, commanding others alſo to aſſiſt them (but were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to do it themſelves, and then carried me to a houſe in the Town, where they kept me cloſe priſoner for the ſpace of above two hours (while they went to their afternoon exerciſe) ſuffering none to come at me, neither I to ſpeak to any ſo much as through the window; after that I had liberty to go to my Inn until the next day; and then by the Juſtices Order, I was to give bayl, or go to Jayl.</p>
               <p>The next day being come, I appeared before <hi>John Crofts</hi> one of the ſaid Juſtices, with whom there were aſſembled ſeveral Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, the ſaid <hi>Elmes,</hi> with one <hi>Palmer,</hi> and others, who again urged many queſtions to me to inſnare me; and the Juſtice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:199130:45"/>of me bail; but I deſired firſt to know my accuſers, and what evil I had done. He anſwered, that my accuſers were not yet known, neither the accuſations; neither was I to know them till I come to tryal. But, ſaid he, we have ſent warrants about the Countrey to ſummon in ſeveral perſons whom we do believe will be your accuſers; and that we are ſhortly to have a meeting at <hi>Stow,</hi> where the perſons ſummoned are to meet us; after which time if you ſend to me, you ſhall have a Copy of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers names, and alſo the accuſations: In the mean time (ſaid <hi>Crofts</hi>) we have power in our ſelves to bind you to appear, or ſend you to Goal.</p>
               <p>And ſo without any thing being laid to my charge, either by themſelves or others, they according to their own wills, bound me to appear at <hi>Gloceſter</hi> Aſſizes following, to anſwer to what was not yet charged againſt me: and according as the Prieſts and Elders deſired of <hi>Feſtus</hi> judgement againſt <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act 25.14, 15, 16.</note> before his accuſers were come face to face, ſo the ſaid Miniſters then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Juſtices, would have had me been ſent to Goal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was accuſed of any thing; and ſaid, That both I and all that adhear'd to me, deſerved no better place.</p>
               <p>After this, I went the ſame day to <hi>Stow,</hi> where was news of ſeveral other Miniſters of the ſame Country then come to Town to enquire concerning me, ſome of which were my former accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers at <hi>Worceſter</hi> and at <hi>Oxford:</hi> And I being again deſired by many people of the Town and Pariſh of <hi>Stow,</hi> went again into the ſtreet, and there preached that day; after which I took my leave of the people, rejoycing that the Lord for carrying on ſo good a work, had again choſen me as an inſtrument in his hand, to bear witneſs to the truth, and ſuffer ſhame for his name.</p>
               <p>And now, my Lord, after the conſideration of all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going diſcourſe, let it pleaſe your Highneſs to do what to your own wiſdom ſhall ſeem meet, that your practice may anſwer your title, even to protect the innocent from thoſe that would devour them; for there are many wolves in lambs clothing, who under the pretence of ſtanding for the truth, and the faith once delivered to the Saints, do perſecute the pure appearances of God in his people;
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3</note> like unto thoſe which <hi>Timothy</hi> ſpeaks of, who <hi>having a form of godlineſs, deny the power thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore I being perſwaded of your Highneſs's tender care
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:199130:45"/>towards ſuch as love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity and truth, was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned in boldneſs to preſent this unto your Highneſs, to right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inform you of the rigorous and illegal proceedings of ſome mennow in power, who under a form of godlineſs, do envy the pure appearances of Jeſus Chriſt in ſpirit and truth: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as the eye of Jeſus is continually toward thoſe that love him, for good; and that <hi>in all their afflictions he is afflicted;</hi> ſo you may be like Jeſus Chriſt, in tendering thoſe that are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in his ſight, that ſo the beloved of the Lord may lie down in ſafety.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, as it hath pleaſed the Lord to advance your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs above your Brethren, for their protection, preſervation and deliverance, as he did <hi>Joſeph</hi> above his brethren, when he made him Lord of all <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, and Ruler throughout all the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> ſo you (like him) may not always be as a ſtranger to your poor, grieved and oppreſſed brethren, to try them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 45.</note> but that you (like <hi>Joſeph</hi>) may alſo make your ſelf known to them, by doing good for them, to comfort and relieve them in their ſeveral wants and neceſſities, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did his brethren, that ſo you may not onely be bleſſed in the Lord, but that both this and after-generations may alſo call you Bleſſed, according as it is written, <hi>The memory of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 10, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>July 1. 1654.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>So waiting upon what the Lord ſhall be pleaſed to direct your Highneſs to do, in reference to theſe particulars, I remain,</hi> Yours to ſerve you in the Lord,<hi>Richard Coppin.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Authors Tryal at</hi> Gloceſter <hi>Aſſizes, before Serjeant</hi> Glyn'; <hi>and the unjuſt proceedings of two Juſtices,</hi> John Crofts, <hi>and</hi> Richard Aylworth <hi>againſt him, the</hi> 22 <hi>of</hi> July, 1654.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>VPon the day and year above written, I made my appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at <hi>Gloceſter</hi> Aſſizes, there expecting a tryal with my
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:199130:46"/>then two adverſaries <hi>Joh. Crofts</hi> &amp; <hi>Richard Aylworth,</hi> two Juſtices of the Peace for that County, who themſelves were there with many Miniſters of the ſame County, conferring together con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what they might inform againſt me, having nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for nothing juſtly could they find then; but their malice being great, the Juſtices with the ſaid Miniſters had fram'd a ſcandalous Paper, in which were many falſe and ſcandalous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations of their own inventions, as a map of malice, which they preſented to the Court, to which was onely the name of <hi>John Crofts,</hi> and to which they themſelves durſt not ſwear, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could they get any other, though they ſought much for it; which particulars were as follow;</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The Information.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>FIrſt, That I had ſeveral times cauſed to come together to hear me, a very great multitude of wicked and prophane people, to the diſturbance of the peace.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly, That I diſturbed their Miniſter in the Church, and that ſome of my company ſhould call out to have the Miniſter pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down, ſaying, Touch</hi> Coppin <hi>who dare.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly, That believers need not pray for the pardon of ſin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fourthly, That there was no heaven nor hell, but belief and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fifthly, That I ſhould call to the people to ſtand to their liberty, and not to ſuffer the Juſtices to entrench upon it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sixthly, That I would not obey the Juſtices Authority.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Seventhly, That I was a continual breaker of the peace.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And now I being called into the Court on Saturday night, a little before the Court roſe, the informations againſt me were read; but nothing of it being proved, there was no anſwer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of me; and the Judge being removed to the other Court, my accuſers would have been my Judges, and alſo witneſſes for themſelves; but I excepted againſt them, and the Court re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them.</p>
               <p>Then I declared againſt their informations, ſhewing them to be falſe, and they themſelves to be no true Chriſtians living in the faith of the Lord Jeſus, ſo long as they did inform againſt, or proſecute any for their judgements; whereupon their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings upon the informations were ſtopt.</p>
               <p>Then they preſented to the Court ſeveral books with my name
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:199130:46"/>to them: And the Court demanded of me, if I would own them. To which I anſwered, That I had written ſuch books, with ſuch titles; but whether thoſe particular books they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced were the ſame I writ, I knew not, unleſs I heard them all read. And I further ſaid, That if they had any thing againſt me, for breach of any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw, I deſired them to proceed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law, and I would further anſwer them. Whereupon the Court told them, That they could proceed no further by theſe informations; but if they had any thing to accuſe me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, they were to proceed by way of indictment.</p>
               <p>But my accuſers not yet knowing with what more to charge me, deſired to know of the Court if they might not indict me for diſturbing their Miniſter in the Church. The Court anſwered They could not do ſo the Miniſter having done before I began, and therefore it could not be proved any diſturbance. But ſaid the Court, If you can pick any thing forth of the books which you ſay are his, and prove it to be blaſphemy, you may indict him for that, proving firſt that he ſaw every line of the books printed: But at this my accuſers were much daunted, knowing not how to prove any thing againſt me, and ſo could not find any thing juſtly to accuſe me. Whereupon they deſired longer time, until Monday; which time the Court granted them.</p>
               <p>And now Monday being come, I was again called into the Court before the Judge; where the ſaid Juſtices, my accuſers, were preſent, but no Miniſter with them, for they were onely the ſetters on of the Juſtices: who then proceeded as before, and finding nothing more againſt me, the foreſaid informations were again read: But the Judge perceiving them to be in malice, and there being no proof to them, he ſeem'd to ſlight them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, He did not like informations in ſuch a nature; to which my accuſers anſwering not; I then deſired to ſpeak my ſelf (though I might have chuſed, there being nothing proved againſt me) and the Judge giving me leave, I declared unto him in open Court the ſubſtance of the whole buſineſs acted againſt me by the ſaid Juſtices at <hi>Stow,</hi> as is before written at large; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by proved my accuſers themſelves to be guilty of what they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed againſt me; and for the proof of which I would have produced ſeveral witneſſes that were then preſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the Judge anſwered, he was already ſatisfied in what I had ſaid, that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:199130:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>the wrong was done to me, and therefore deſired no further witneſs.</p>
               <p>Then my accuſers again urged the books. To which I anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as before, naming the ſeveral titles of the books I had written. Out of which books my accuſers had pick'd here and there ſome part of ſome particular ſentences, which they preferred to the Judge to examine me upon. But the Judge, after he had read it, told them, that they had given him that which was non-ſenſe in taking part of a ſentence, and not the whole; for in ſo doing (ſaid he) you may wrong the ſenſe of any mans words; and you are not to do ſo; but you are to take the words before, and the words after, and then the one might explain the other, as ſaid the Judge. To which my accuſers were ſilent: ſo nothing at all being proved againſt me, the Judge asked them, what my life and converſation was; againſt which they alſo had nothing to ſay. Then they gave the Judge a note of my former accuſations at <hi>Oxford,</hi> declaring that I had ſince ſpoke the ſame things; and ſo importuned the Judge to keep me bound till the next Aſſizes. But the Judge told them, he could do no ſuch thing, unleſs they could prove that I had tranſgreſſed the Law: and, ſaid he, for that which ye reckoned an offence already committed by him, which for my part I cannot, you have already puniſhed him contrary to the Law, in keeping him bound till now.</p>
               <p>And, ſaid the Judge, as touching the accuſations at <hi>Oxford,</hi> I underſtand he there anſwered them before my brother <hi>Green,</hi> then Judge of that Aſsize, and I am not to queſtion him any more upon that; therefore unleſs you have any thing againſt him, he ought to be freed.</p>
               <p>But nothing elſe could they find, though they ſought and tryed every way for it, to the uttermoſt of their endeavours. Whereupon I was freed, to the ſhame of my enemies.</p>
               <p>And now what an advantage might I take againſt thoſe men, for the wrong done unto me by them, if I would proceed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law? but my principles lead me to no ſuch thing, as to ſeek revenge againſt any man, but freely to forgive my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and to love them which hate me, as Chriſt in me gives me Commandment; and in ſo doing, though in many things I ſuffer, yet in God I find reſt for my ſoul.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:199130:47"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
